<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A treatise of prayer. Two quæries resolved touching formes of prayer. And six quæries relating specially to the Lords Prayer. That the reader may have full resolution, specially to the fourth of these quæries, relating to the Lords Prayer, he shall find in the end of this treatise, that holy and learned mans judgement, Dr. Owen, as to that matter in his answer to Mr Biddles second question of prayer. Pag.667, 668, 669.</title>
            <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1656</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 205 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 42 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2013-12">2013-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A96904</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing W3508</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Thomason E880_9</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R206598</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99865718</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99865718</idno>
            <idno type="VID">117967</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A96904)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 117967)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Thomason Tracts ; 132:E880[9])</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A treatise of prayer. Two quæries resolved touching formes of prayer. And six quæries relating specially to the Lords Prayer. That the reader may have full resolution, specially to the fourth of these quæries, relating to the Lords Prayer, he shall find in the end of this treatise, that holy and learned mans judgement, Dr. Owen, as to that matter in his answer to Mr Biddles second question of prayer. Pag.667, 668, 669.</title>
                  <author>Woodward, Ezekias, 1590-1675.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>[2], 78 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by M.S. for Henry Cripps in Popes-head Alley,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London, :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1656.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Attributed to Ezekias Woodward.</note>
                  <note>Annotation on Thomason copy: "June.2".</note>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the British Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Owen, John, 1616-1683 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Biddle, John, 1618-1662 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Lord's Prayer --  Early works to 1800.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-04</date>
            <label>Apex CoVantage</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-06</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2013-02</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:117967:1"/>
            <p>A TREATISE OF PRAYER.</p>
            <p>Two <hi>Quaeries</hi> reſolved touching formes of Prayer. And Six <hi>Quaeries</hi> relating ſpecially to the LORDS PRAYER.</p>
            <p>That the Reader may have full Reſolution, ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially to the fourth of theſe <hi>Queries,</hi> relating to the Lords Prayer, he ſhall finde in the end of this Trea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tiſe, That Holy and Learned Mans judgement, D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
               <hi>Owen,</hi> as to that matter in his Anſwer to Mr <hi>Biddles</hi> ſecond queſtion of Prayer <hi>Pag.</hi> 667, 668, 669.</p>
            <q>
               <p>
                  <hi>They who aske not for the Spirit, that they may pray in the Spirit, are <gap reason="foreign">
                        <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
                     </gap>, Brutes and Mutes.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Chry:</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>A Malefactor expecting his ſentence to death, needs not man or booke to prompt him how to plead for his life. He that can reade himſelfe Caſt and condemned by ſinne, needs not a booke to prompt him how to plead his pardon.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Pariſ: of Divine Rhetor: Compare with this <hi>Jer:</hi> 3. 13. and <hi>Rom:</hi> 10. 9, 10.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>The Lords Prayer is the mould, wherein all the Churches prayers are caſt, moulded and formed:</hi> 
                  <bibl>Bez: Luk. 11. 2.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>See to it, that God be as well pleaſed with thee calling Him Father, as thou art well pleaſed to call Him Father.</hi> 
                  <bibl>Cyp: Sermon the ſixt upon the Lords prayer: <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</bibl>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Thou ſhalt call me My father, and ſhalt not turne away from Me,</hi> 
                  <bibl>Jer: 3. 19.</bibl> [that is, I will put filiall affections, awfull thoughts, conſtant reſolutions into thy heart, and <hi>thou ſhalt not turne away from Me</hi>].</p>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>London,</hi> Printed by <hi>M. S.</hi> for <hi>Henry Cripps</hi> in <hi>Popes-head-Alley,</hi> 1656.</p>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="treatise">
            <pb facs="tcp:117967:2"/>
            <pb n="1" facs="tcp:117967:2"/>
            <head>THE FOURTH TREATISE OF PRAYER.</head>
            <argument>
               <p>Two <hi>Queries</hi> touching formes of Prayer, and ſix relating to the Lords Prayer. I. Whether a wicked man may ſay that prayer? II. Whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther our Lord gave His Diſciples this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, that they ſhould pray to His Father in thoſe very words? III. Whether a Godly man takes it into his Cloſet? IV. Whether it be comely for a Godly Miniſter to take it into his pulpit? V. Whether <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to pray, by giving them <hi>formes</hi> of pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to ſay? VI. Whether a Godly parent can teach his childe to pray, by giving him any forme of prayer? And in ſpeciall, by teaching his childe to ſay the Lords Prayer?</p>
               <p>The Negative in all theſe is under our Maintenance.</p>
            </argument>
            <div n="1" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. I.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE ſhall not enter into the Common place of prayer, it is not a place to ſay much of it; and to ſay little is to ſay little more than nothing at all. It is, being mounted on the wheele of Faith, the great Engine of the world, and wheeles all about there; it is an <hi>Appeale to God</hi> in the Name and Mediation of Chriſt; A committing the cauſe and Condition of
<pb n="2" facs="tcp:117967:3"/> His Church, and of His Truth, the concernements thereof in Generall, His owne in ſpeciall, to Him, and ſo takeing faſt hold of the Allmightie, the Allſufficient God in Chriſt, it hath an <hi>Omnipotency</hi> in it, and can doe what God Himſelfe is pleaſed to doe, <hi>all things,</hi> that ſtand with His good will and pleaſure for the ſupport and ſupply of His Church, every faithfull ſoule there: And the carying on of His <hi>Truth,</hi> whereby <hi>immortality and light is brought to light in the ſoule.</hi> In a word, It is the breathing-in and-out of the Spirit of God and of Glory; It is that which fet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth-in all from God through the hand of Chriſt by the Spirit; And the Returne of All to God the firſt ſpring and fountaine of all by the ſame way of Conveyance: For he or ſhe, that Remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers they have all from God, cannot forget to Returne all to Him. The Diſciple hath all by askeing, and it is but aske and have, the ſame he asketh, or that which is better; he writeth up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>onall he hath, <hi>Asked of God, The Gift of God;</hi> His Lord and Ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter<note place="margin">Pſal 2. Math. 26.</note> had nothing but by askeing, <hi>Aske of Me,</hi> and <hi>I will give thee.</hi> And that He, the Mediator of His Church, giveth-out unto His people at this preſent, He asketh His Father firſt. Surely the Saint muſt aske in Faith, if he will receive in mercy; for ſo he ask<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth His Lords leave, and acknowledgeth Him to be Lord of the <hi>Mannour</hi> of <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                  </hi> and <hi>Earth.</hi> To ſhutt up this, and to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed to what we cheifly intend in this place; Prayers are the Em<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>baſſadours of the poo<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap> empty ſoule, to God for ſupply from the aboundant Riches of His grace: We ſay a poore empty Spirit, for that is full of prayer, and much ſupplication <hi>The poore man</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Prov. 18. 23.</note> 
                  <hi>ſpeakes ſupplications,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> intreaties, that is his Character and his Dialect. But <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 words">
                     <desc>〈◊◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> is no ſenſe of povertie, there is no prayer, for there is a <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> temper, Rich enough and wanting</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>nothing;</hi> That perſon prayeth not, or not to purpoſe, it is but a Cuſtome onely and a forme.</p>
               <p>Now we crave leave to put two Queſtions, and humbly to give our perſwaſion in way of Anſwer unto both.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>1. WHether perſons full of themſelves, as we are all by na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, wholy emptie and ſwept of all Goodneſſe, and garniſhed with noyſome luſts, the furniture and rich garniſh of<note place="margin">Math. 12. 44.</note>
                     <pb n="3" facs="tcp:117967:3"/> the uncleane Spirits houſe, whether theſe are like to helpe them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves by uſeing ſett formes of Prayer?</p>
                  <p>2. Whether <hi>Babes</hi> in Chriſt, newly converted ones, renewed in the <hi>Spirit of their mindes,</hi> have need of <hi>formes,</hi> thoſe crutches and helpes of devotion, when they are addreſſing themſelves un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to their God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>The firſt;</hi> Whether unreaſonable and wicked men, as all are, that have not faith, can helpe themſelves in this their condition by uſeing ſett formes of prayer?</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> To this we humbly give our opinion, That they cannot helpe themſelves at all, but the more they uſe them, the more they are diſadvantaged by them, the more indiſpoſed to, and putt fur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther off from the power of Godlineſſe. For</p>
                  <p>Firſt, The reaſon of this we take from the Philoſophers knowne rule, which indeed we thinke falls-in with common Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perience, <q>That <hi>habits,</hi> whether in good things or in evill, are acquired and improved both by continuall exerciſe.</q> Theſe things, which we learne <hi>for</hi> practiſe, we learne <hi>by</hi> practiſe, as ſaith learned D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> 
                     <hi>Wilkins.</hi> Now for any one to habituate or accuſtome himſelfe to formes of prayer, that is, to prayers made or written by another, and ſaid by himſelfe, ſhall find himſelfe as unable, and as hard a matter to come off from them (yet off he muſt come i<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ever he looke to find acceptance with his God) as it is with an <hi>Ethiopian</hi> to change his skin, or the Leopard his ſpots. O! we are much taken with and hardly taken off from <hi>formes of prayer,</hi> we have been accuſtomed to from our youth up, and never found theſe did the fleſh any hurt, putting <hi>it to Coſt;</hi> as theſe never did the ſpirit or <hi>hid-man</hi> of the heart any good. So then theſe formes of prayer we come with before God, doe more indiſpoſe us to God, and eſtrange us from Him: And it is not good to accuſtome our ſelves to that, we muſt leave at laſt, and come off from, if ever good be wrought in us or by us.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Becauſe we may ſay of theſe formes of prayer, as is ſaid of the wicked themſelves, theſe are <hi>ſenſuall not having the</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jude 19.</note> 
                     <hi>Spirit:</hi> though we may ſuppoſe them very exactly compoſed; and by the moſt accompliſhed Men, we meane, by Holy men, <hi>having the Spirit.</hi> For though they might <hi>pray in prayer, wrought</hi> by the Spirit for that very thing; Yet being written before their
<pb n="4" facs="tcp:117967:4"/> eyes, and prayed by the booke <hi>viſible</hi> or <hi>inviſible,</hi> we meane the <hi>memory,</hi> there is no more ſpirit and life therein, than there is in a dead letter. Indeed we may call theſe prayers <hi>fleſh,</hi> being writ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten with inke <hi>which profiteth nothing,</hi> it is the <hi>Spirit that quick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neth;</hi> And thereby, that is by the <hi>Spirit of God,</hi> His people call <hi>Him Father,</hi> and <hi>Jeſus their Lord.</hi> But praying without the <hi>Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit,</hi> and wholy careleſſe to aske after the <hi>Spirit,</hi> calling for it in prayer, we are never more likely than at ſuch a time, and when we are upon that ſolemne worke, never more likely than then to call <hi>Chriſt accurſed.</hi> Could we ſay, <hi>Abraham's, Iſaac's, Jacob's</hi>
                     <note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Cor. 12. 3.</note> prayers, with <hi>Paul's</hi> prayers, &amp;c. And have not that Spirit, by which they prayed, our prayers would become as we beleeve, in the eares of our God, but as <hi>ſounding braſſe or a tinkling Cym<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ball.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, We may Conſider this. All that God giveth to us, or workes for us, He doth all by the Hand of His Spirit: So alſo, All that His people give backe againe to Him, or worke for Him, They doe it by the ſpeciall helpe of the Spirit too; Therefore it is they ſee ſo much need of the Spirit, and call ſo earneſtly for a ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plie from the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 1. But it may be ſaid, how ſhall ſenſuall men, not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Spirit call for the Spirit; unleſſe as they are taught to doe it in other's words?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> This is a leſſon can never be taught by man, not by all or any prayers ſuggeſted to us by Man; That every one of us by Nature is the Devill's houſe emptied and ſwept of all Goodneſſe, brim-full of all filthineſſe, adorned and garniſhed with noiſome luſts, the ornament and garniſh of that houſe the Devill calls his owne; this we thinke no man queſtioneth. Now if all this were debated upon and ſet downe prayer-wiſe, according to the ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>acteſt forme, It could not accompliſh the thing: what is it to ſay in another's <hi>words, I am a ſinner,</hi> or <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> though, ſaying<note place="margin">Job 5. 20.</note> ſo much, he had ſaid all, if his heart had ſaid it, and not another for him, <hi>freely, feelingly, ſincerely</hi> and <hi>beleivingly:</hi> So then one word ſpoken in deſire and endeavour from the heart, as aforeſaid, hath more virtue and efficacy in it, than a thouſand words ſug<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>geſted to us by the eyes or memory onely. Certainly we muſt confeſſe ſinne in our owne words, our Confeſſion will not be ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cepted
<pb n="5" facs="tcp:117967:4"/> elſe; as we muſt forſake ſin in our workes; they, that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe and forſake ſin, are the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 2. But is there not a double uſe of theſe ſet formes of prayer? firſt, for directing of our deſires? ſecondly, for execite<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing our affections?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> We humbly conceive there is not a ſingle uſe of them; not firſt for the directing our deſires. Theſe are all inward and are moved by a principle within, never ſtirred to move after God, Chriſt, Grace, Glory, till there be ſome inward ſenſe, or feeling of the want, and neceſſitie of haveing God in Chriſt, and all the needs of the ſoule ſupplyed by Him. <hi>Senſe of want is the Giving of Deſire.</hi> Now we cannot ſee how this inward ſenſe can be wrought in the Soule, by a forme of words lying before us, any more than painted bread can ſtirre-up deſire, or ſatisfie deſire be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing ſtirred-up. As no outward thing can inwardly defile, for all reall and truely called defilement is within and from within, elſe the Devill himſelfe could not defile us; ſo no outward thing can inwardly purifie; and then, not purifying, it can give but poore directions, to our deſires. Secondly, Nor are they of uſe, (as we conceive) for the exciteing our affections: Theſe are warme and hott and doe heate and warme, but ſtill by ſome workings from within firſt. Affection is like fire, it is hot it ſelfe firſt, before it heate others; We muſt be affected before we can affect. Now we cannot ſee how a dead powerleſſe forme (which as one hath it, nouriſheth the <hi>hid-man of the heart,</hi> no more than <hi>ſtock-fiſh</hi> nou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>riſheth the bodie, and that gives no more nouriſhment, ſaith <hi>E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>raſmus,</hi> than a ſtone does) can excite affections, unleſſe to it ſelfe, becauſe ſo exceeding pleaſing to fleſh and blood, never croſſing in the leaſt the Deſires of the ſame.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 3. But is not this to take the generalitie of men quite off from praying?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> No: to our ſeeming it putts them on upon prayer, to pray that they may be enabled to pray in a deepe ſenſe of ſinne, and the need they have of the blood of Chriſt to purifie their hearts, and pacifie their Conſciences; all which they are to pray for.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 4. But pray they cannot, unleſſe they pray by the booke, viſible or inviſible.</p>
                  <pb n="6" facs="tcp:117967:5"/>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> To this we ſay, That to our ſeeming if they doe pray by the booke, they doe not pray at all in Gods account. And truely thoſe men are b<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>lder with God than they durſt be with men; had they offended a great Lord, they muſt acknowledge the offence with their owne mouthes, and not another for them, and have righted their offended Lord, if he would have it ſo, with their owne hands; and glad with all their hearts, that the offended Lord would be ſo accorded; But we are bold with God though who made us ſo, but our owne ſhameleſſe impudent Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits? We can offend God ſinning againſt Him, and confeſſe it by a <hi>proxi,</hi> in his words who did not give the offence. We ſin with our owne mouthes, and will confeſſe with anothers mouth: may not the Lord ſay, <hi>offer this to your Governour, ſee whether he will</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mal: 1. 18.</note> 
                     <hi>accept of your Perſon?</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 5. But this will be ſaid ſtill, if they may not pray by the booke they cannot pray at all ſo the Lord God ſhall have no ſervice from them at all?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> Indeed the Lord God, to Whome all we are, and have, and can, is due, hath no ſervice, none at all from a wicked man, his <hi>luſts</hi> are deepe ſharers here, for they have all; as once ſo they ſay ſtill, <hi>It is in vaine to ſerve the Lord.</hi> But all the Diſſervice<note place="margin">Mal. 3. 14.</note> they can doe, they doe unto the Lord, even all they can againſt Him, becauſe they know Him not; for this is a Ruled Caſe, or a knowne Concluſion; <q>The more we know of God, the more we honour Him, and our ſelves the leſſe; And the leſſe we know of God, the leſſe we honour Him, and our ſelves the more; As God riſeth in our thoughts, ſo we fall, and as we riſe in our owne thoughts, ſo God falls.</q> We would adde this, That the hardneſſe of our hearts appeares in nothing more than in theſe ſtout words, <hi>We cannot pray, our Spirits are ſo barren;</hi> Theſe are ſtout words indeed, and argue the ſtouteſt heart, and much pride of Spirit, as uſually ſpoken by proud Men; It is as if ſo be a man ſhould ſay; <hi>I ſinne and I will ſinne: But I will not ſay unto God I have ſinned, what ſhall I doe?</hi> If He will take my Confeſſion from another's-mouth, let Him take it; I will not confeſſe my ſelfe a ſinner, with my owne Mouth; nor will I aske Him pardon. Theſe are as ſtout words, to our ſeeming, as can be ſpoken; upon the Readers thoughts we leave them. When we have added this
<pb n="7" facs="tcp:117967:5"/> more; As we are Creatures, and have our dependance upon God, every moment we are obliged to pray unto Him: As ſinfull Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, ſuch as ſin and Satan can make us, we are obliged to con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>feſſe unto Him with our own Mouths. We would anſwer a Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion one or two more before we give Reſolution to the other Caſe.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 6. <q>But would not praemeditated formes prevent many rude, Crude or indigeſted expreſſions?</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> Yes ſure, with thoſe, that know not in the world how to pray without them; <hi>If ſenſuall men not having the Spirit,</hi> wholy carried by ſenſe, and minding nothing above the place their foote treades on, if theſe ſhould pray without the booke, poſſibly, as their parts might be, low and meane, they would uſe ſtrange and uncouth expreſſions. But they, who ſet themſelves before their God, and expect the ſupplies of His Spirit from Him, looking upon their owne ſtrength as rottenneſſe, to be reſted on; knowing they cannot thinke a good thought, as of themſelves, and would not for a world utter raſh words in His preſence; ſurely they ſhall finde the aſſiſtance they looke for, and ſuch a ſupplie as ſhall be beſt for them; And if they riſe not from their knees more comforted, They ſhall be more humbled, which is as good; for a groane from the heart is as good as a teare from the<note place="margin">The Spirit of adoption may be in a groane as well as in a prayer. <hi>Mr. Ford. ſp. Ador. 480.</hi>
                     </note> eye; And they ſhall be kept from ſpeaking that in prayer, which is unbecomeing their God to heare; or the Asking of that, which is unbeſeeming their God to grant. But we would add this, which we thinke more properly relates to the Reſolution of this Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion. A wicked mans prayer, we meane him, who is reſolved to goe-on in his wickedneſſe, comes from his neceſſities, feare and dread being before him, trouble and anguiſh upon him, perhaps and terrour within him, looking upon death now not at a di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance, but as the <hi>King of terrours, requiring his ſoule of him, and killing him with death:</hi> his prayer now, as we were ſaying, comes from his neceſſities, not from his heart, therefore ſhall not come <hi>neare Gods heart</hi> (to ſpeake after the manner of men) And then it is all one whether he pray by the book, or by his owne Spirit, the one as the other hath the ſame acceptance with God. <hi>Deare children, followers of God</hi> alwayes, are alwayes heard, though they doe but <hi>chatter like a Crane.</hi> And children of <hi>Belial,</hi> who never
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:117967:6"/> heard God ſpeaking unto them in His Word, are not heard of God, for He heareth not ſuch ſinners, who wallow in their ſinne as doth a ſwine in the myre, and returne unto it as doth a dog to his vomit. Whether then their expreſſions are exact, and as well compoſed as words in print can be: or rude, indigeſted or incom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſed, it is much the ſame, and comes to as much as nothing. Such a wicked-mans praying is but tatling, and babling; or to ſpeake as the holy Scripture doth, It is as the <hi>roaring of Beares,</hi> or <hi>howling of Doggs,</hi> Iſa. 59. 11. Hoſ. 7. 14.</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt:</hi> 7. Moreover, It is ſaid, doe not they, who dare not bring praemeditated formes before their God, ruſh upon dutie, without uſeing the Common meanes of fitting themſelves, and ſo tempt God?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> To this we ſay, that to expect any thing from God, without uſeing the meanes allowed by God, as helpes that way, were to tempt God and provoke Him to His face; Therefore doubtleſſe it is the wicked man that ruſhes upon Dutie, not be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thinking himſelfe before-hand unto what a glorious preſence he is come, and what is the worke he is to engage upon, and what the danger is of miſcarrying; He that thinkes of none of all this, he Ruſheth upon Dutie; And indeed what needs the meditation of what I am to ſpeake unto God, when it is ſuggeſted unto me? I can reade it with mine eyes, and ſee my ſelfe ſpeake? But that man, that prayeth in the Spirit, though he doth make a totall re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſignation of himſelfe unto the hands of the Spirit, expecting His immediate ſuggeſtions, Yet ſo as he hath omitted no meanes be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore to fit and prepare for that high ſervice; as thoughts of him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe and his nothingneſs; of the glorious Name of God, and all his expectations, therein and from the ſame: Theſe things toge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther with the word of God, he gives himſelfe to, meditates upon, and is <hi>wholy in it,</hi> and is ſo as the ſeaſon fitts, he addreſſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe before his God: He knowes, That, that glorious promiſe, <hi>Math: 10. 19. Take no thought how or what ye ſhall ſpeake, for it ſhall be given you in the ſame houre;</hi> relateth to extraordinary ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices, when God calls forth unto them, that then they may expect extraordinarie aſſiſtance. But when he may uſe Common and or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dinarie means of Gods appointment to prepare him for this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing worke, and ſhould be negligent in the uſe thereof, which
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:117967:6"/> through grace he cannot br, then it were a great preſumption to depend upon extraordinary helpe; So now before we come to give ſome reſolution to the Second <hi>Querie,</hi> we would in the cloſe of this, give-in ſome Counſell, which we hope ſhall be well agree<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with the word of God, to them, who being <hi>ſenſuall not ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving the Spirit,</hi> muſt needs be wholy unacquainted, with the <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Chriſt,</hi> who is the <hi>way,</hi> the <hi>Truth,</hi> and the <hi>life,</hi> and yet hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, they pray to God, and praiſe Him, as ordinarily as they riſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>up from their Beds, and Tables; lye downe upon the one, and ſit at the other. This is the Counſell we would give, That they would ceaſe from their <hi>formes</hi> of praying, or from praying by a <hi>forme,</hi> which differs as much from <hi>praying in the Holy Ghoſt,</hi> as doth the <hi>Sunne</hi> in the <hi>firmament,</hi> from the <hi>Sunne</hi> painted on a ſigne-poſt: And apply themſelves to <hi>hearing the Word,</hi> whereby faith cometh-in to the ſoule; ſo may they, by the bleſſing of God, attaine to the knowledge of Him, to whom they are praying; and of Him in whoſe Name they muſt pray, and find <hi>acceſſe unto the Father;</hi> of Him alſo through whoſe <hi>interceſſion</hi> within us the prayer is formed (<hi>Rom.</hi> 8. 26.) and ſo finds acceptance, by the <hi>Mediation</hi> of that <hi>Advocate</hi> with-out us, at the right hand of the Father, being as <hi>ſweet Odours</hi> now, all that from the fleſh adhe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring to them, being ſeperated from them. Hereby alſo, we meane by <hi>diligent hearing the Word preached,</hi> they may attaine to a knowledge of themſelves, what <hi>loſt-ones</hi> they are in themſelves, and that they muſt be <hi>puniſhed with everlaſting deſtruction from the preſence of the Lord, and from the glory of His power,</hi> if they <hi>know not God, and obey not the Goſpel of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt,</hi> and <hi>be found in Him;</hi> which may put them upon praying that they may profit by hearing. Indeed we would take off theſe <hi>ſenſuall perſons, not having the Spirit from praying by the booke;</hi> and <hi>Read<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing the Holy Scriptures,</hi> as they read them; and apply themſelves to the <hi>hearing Gods Word in ſeaſon and out of ſeaſon,</hi> and attend upon the moovings of the Holy Spirit, upon the Word preached, which is the Chariot of the Spirit, therewith (for ſo it is appoin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted of God) the good Spirit comes into the heart, as the Sunne into the houſe; workes Faith there, and makes us light in the Lord: ſo as now we can ſee clearely how to pray, and how to read, and ſet our ſeale to it; whereas before we did not pray, nor
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:117967:7"/> did <hi>read the booke, neither did we looke thereon</hi> 
                     <note n="*" place="margin">Revel. 5. 4. See <hi>Bright.</hi>
                     </note>. We ſay it againe, this is the Counſell, which hath been given to us, and, through mercy, we have received it, and therefore we would give it to o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, who may be (as we were when time was) as much verſed in reading the Holy Scriptures, as they are in praying, and all this while, as we did, ſlighting the place appointed for Hearing, and deſpiſing the Word preached there. Thus then, as we were ſay<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, we would adviſe them to <hi>frequent Sermons,</hi> and give all Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence to <hi>profit</hi> thereby, we meane, to get faith by hearing, that therewith they may <hi>mixe</hi> that they heare, and make it profitable unto them. For if we enquire at the <hi>Holy Oracle,</hi> we beleeve it will reſolve us, as to <hi>Reading</hi> the Holy Scriptures before we have profited by <hi>Hearing,</hi> That the word of God preached, which is called, we thinke, <hi>The ſword of the Spirit,</hi> is as different from the <hi>Word</hi> read in our houſe, as is a ſword in the hand of a Mighty man, different, in point of working, or making execution upon our luſts, from the ſword lifted-up in <hi>Georges</hi> hand upon a ſigne-poſt. Give we then all Diligence in Hearing, that we may read and pray at home with underſtanding. This is our Counſell, and this our Concluſion, That, whoſoever rejecteth it, <hi>multiplies Tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſſions,</hi> as he multiplies prayers, and praiſes. Nor can he think, and ſhew himſelfe a man, That he ſhall <hi>be taught of the Father,</hi> who <hi>heareth not His Word:</hi> or that Chriſt appeares in the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſence of God for him in heaven; when he viſibly and apparently appeares againſt Him on earth, turning His Word behind his back, and ſetting his heart againſt it. We proceed to the ſecond <hi>Querie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Q:</hi> II. <q>WHether Babes in Chriſt, newly converted ones, renewed in the ſpirit of their mindes, have need of formes, thoſe commonly called crutches and helpes of Devotion when they appeare before their God?</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> We humbly conceive, no: If they that were Lame be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore cannot now <hi>leape like an Hart,</hi> yet they can goe to God without a Crutch. And this we thinke the Scripture holds forth before us, that the <hi>Adopted of God in Chriſt,</hi> His Sonnes and
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:117967:7"/> Daughters, have out-growne their Crutches and helpes of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>votion, though ſome of them but <hi>Babes</hi> in Chriſt. For whenſoe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver The <hi>Spirit</hi> tells a perſon, he is the ſonne or daughter of God, having wrought faith in his heart; The ſecond thing the <hi>Spirit</hi> doth, it teacheth him to pray, that is, to <hi>Call God Father,</hi> which is the voice of Gods Spirit in a ſanctified ſoule; It enableth him<note place="margin">G<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>la. 4. 6<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> to Cry <hi>Abba Father:</hi> to pray earneſtly, to be fervent in prayer; They were cold prayers before, but a lip-labour onely; But the Spirit, comeing-in to witneſſe with his Spirit, and bringing faith with Him, makes the Childe to goe to God, and looke upon Him as a <hi>Father,</hi> whoſe favour he doubts not off; or if he doe, he would have his doubts reſolved, and his evidences cleared; and for this he <hi>cries;</hi> and is not helped at all, as we conceive, by any ſet forme, which heateth the Spirit no more than the <hi>Cenſer</hi> is without fire; for the Holy Ghoſt having ſanctified the heart, and put it into a whole-frame of Grace; The heart ſpeakes to God as it is quickned, acted, and moved by the Spirit of God: And herein we would appeale to the experience and practiſe of all, that are but <hi>Babes</hi> in Chriſt, whether ever they were gainers, by any formes of Devotion, prayers ſett before them? And if they ſay, no; then they will not be eaſily perſwaded to pray by thoſe formes, from which they gaine nothing but more dullneſſe, droſſineſſe and indiſpoſedneſſe in their Spirits. It is our perſwa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion, That a child of God, who is afflicted with the ſenſe of ſinne, and affected with the ſenſe of a pardon, had rather ſpeake five words to God with his underſtanding and ſutable affections, than ten thouſand words prompted or ſuggeſted to him by a viſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble<note place="margin">Books are a memory with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out us, and memory is a book within<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> us.</note> booke, before his eye, or an inviſible, his memory; And more acceptance ſhould he find with his God. He hath told his errand in his owne words; perhaps he wants words and can but chatter, like a Crane: It is, as was ſaid, a prayer notwithſtanding, and may crie aloud in the eares of his God; It is delivered with under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, with ſuitable affections<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with Humility, an excellent in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gredient in prayer, with an inward ſenſe of his Condition; It is a good prayer ſure and finds acceptance with his God. We are ge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerally deceived about prayer, It is, thinke we, a worke of memo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie, of a good witt, a readie invention, a voluble tongue, This makes an excellent prayer in the eſteeme of a mans ſelfe, and in
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:117967:8"/> the account of others; But this is not prayer; <hi>Prayer is the worke,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ford.</hi> p. 629. 525, 526 545, 546.</note> 
                     <hi>of Gods Spirit, in a ſanctified heart,</hi> and feeles no need of Crutches to ſupport and beare it up Heaven-ward; theſe help us not we find, when we are <hi>lame;</hi> it is granted, theſe hinder us when we are <hi>ſound;</hi> The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> is the Churches Advocate by <hi>Office;</hi> The <hi>Spirit</hi> her Advocate by <hi>Energie</hi> and <hi>operation.</hi> All the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers,<note place="margin">Rom. 8. 26.</note> which prevaile with God are formed, wrought and faſhioned in our hearts by the Spirit of God. Now we ſuppoſe here is a <hi>B<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>be</hi> in Chriſt, as weake as <hi>Babes</hi> are, notwithſtanding he hath<note place="margin">Bez<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </note> no need of a forme; he is in Chriſt, and therefore hath the Spirit of Chriſt, and therefore in the Spirit he can pray. <hi>The Spirit hel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peth his infirmities<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> Rom: 8. 26. <hi>helpeth.</hi> The Greek word is ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry emphaticall, a De-compound, helpeth as a Father helpeth the little Child at a burden; The Child onely puts to his hand, the Father his ſtrength. Indeed the Father doth all, ſo doth the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in this <hi>Babe:</hi> and if any thing elſe come to helpe with Him, He will not helpe at all. If the Crutch doe any thing, the Spirit will doe nothing. <hi>He is an helpe ſufficient of Himſelfe, The Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit will not helpe with a Crutch.</hi> When the Spirit of God ſets home our miſerie and extreame neceſſitie, we cannot want wittie words and Ingenious expreſſions. <hi>Grande doleris ingenium eſt mi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeriſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> venit ſolertia rebus: miſery felt is full of ingenuity, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nergie too:</hi> 
                     <q>It will tell it's tale well enough; the man is ſenſible of his wants, you need not ſupplie him with words. If a poore Tenant, finding he hath a hard bargaine, comes to his Land<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lord, Let him alone for telling his tale, (ſaid excellent <hi>Sibs</hi>) you may warrant his abilitie that way; he will lay open the ſtate of his wife and Children, and the ill yeare he hath had; he will be eloquent enough.</q> There is no man that hath an humble and broken heart (though he be never ſo illeterate) but he will have a large heart to God in this kinde. The great worke in our ſelves is, for the working whereof we muſt attend the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rits worke in the Uſe of the meanes, is a <hi>true ſenſe of our owne ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie:</hi>
                     <note place="margin">See D. <hi>in W.</hi> p. 27.</note> And then we ſhall not need, as the <hi>ſentenced Malefactor</hi> needs not, Any Maſter to teach us how to ſupplicate; nor any booke out of which we might learne a fitt forme of petitioning. The apprehenſion of our preſent danger will make us both im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>portunate and eloquent, in the deſire of mercy. <hi>A ſpring of De<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſire ariſeth from the ſenſe of want.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <pb n="13" facs="tcp:117967:8"/>
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>THus we have told our Apprehenſion in this matter; It were no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> faire dealing now, if we ſhould conceale from the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der, that the Godly learned have ſpoken much in favour of ſet formes of prayer; And the lateſt, we thinke, that have written for them, is Reverend <hi>Hilderſon;</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>I doe not denie,</hi> ſaith he, <hi>but a weake Chriſtian may uſe the helpe of a good prayer booke;</hi> In this<note place="margin">Pſal. 51. 63.</note> caſe <hi>better to pray with a booke, than not to pray at all.</hi> Certainly 'tis a Spirit of Errour that hath taught the world otherwiſe. Firſt our Bleſſed Saviour preſcrib'd to His Diſciples a forme of prayer, not onely to be <hi>to them,</hi> and to His whole Church, a Rule and Samplar, according to which all our prayers ſhould be framed; but even <hi>for them,</hi> and to ſay it, <hi>tying themſelves to the words of it.</hi> Luk. 11. 2. It is cleare alſo that <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray, by giving them formes of Prayer to ſay, And the beſt reformed doe now and ever have, uſed preſcript formes of Prayers, and have judged them of great uſe and ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie for the Edification of the Church:</q> Reverend <hi>Hilderſon's</hi> words all theſe; A man, as all know, of pretious note and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count in the Church, and ſo with all, we thinke, that feare their God; we would be numbered amongſt them in this matter; but for our Reaſon, now that the Lord hath, we hope, ſanctified it; and our Judgement, we reſerve it as a Chaſt Virgin for the Lord; our meaning is, we will not give up our judgement to any man; In deſire and endeavour, through Grace, we will lay that levell to the Rule of God's Word. We will not, we are ſure we ought not to call any man on Earth <hi>Father</hi> or <hi>Maſter,</hi> That is, we will give no man power on Earth over our Judgements and Conſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ences, ſuch the Father hath (or ſeeme to take) over the perſon of his Child. We are to follow none but as they follow Chriſt,<note place="margin">Math. 23. 8, 9.</note> no<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> ought we to be commanded by any, that Command not from His mouth; our Leaders muſt le<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>d to Him, our Commander muſt command for Him, elſe we muſt not be lead, or Commanded by<note place="margin">Iſa. 55. 4.</note> them. My Conſcience, as one <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>aith, is Gods throne, I cannot<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ford. ſp. of Ad. p.</hi> 4<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> 
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> anſwer it to God, if I permit (any man) much leſſe Satan to u<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurp it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="14" facs="tcp:117967:9"/>
                  <p>So now it will be expected we ſhould give ſome account of our diſſenting from thoſe Learned and Godly men in point of ſet formes of prayers. For the ſame we have read from worthy <hi>Hild.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Firſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>ol p 348. Saints e<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>o p. 80.</note> we may read from others the excellent of the Earth, <hi>Perkins; Preſton.</hi> Theſe were for ſett formes; Therefore We profeſſe we are in ſome kinde of paine, while we are declareing our Judge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, which will be ſomewhat differing from theirs in this point, theſe being as is well knowne in all the Earth eminently Learned and Godly. But for the laſt of theſe, That excellent Preacher in his time, Dr: <hi>Preſton,</hi> it may be noted, That he alloweth the practiſe of the primitive times, and of our times, in reference to their <hi>Litur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gies</hi> onely, in their publike meeting places; And tells us, it is not enough to be preſent at and joyne in theſe prayers, but we muſt Goe to God in ſecret, and <q>
                        <hi>he that is exceeding weake,</hi>
                     </q> that is his<note place="margin">See Mr. <hi>Ford</hi> of Adop: 525, 526. 545, 545.</note> expreſſion, may uſe a <hi>prop to helpe him,</hi> as a Child that cannot goe, he meanes a ſett forme of prayer for a time; In the next place it may be obſerved of them both, That they take in this <hi>obi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter,</hi> and as it were upon the by; It was not to their ſcope, and therefore not in their purpoſe or intention to plead by way of Ar<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gument for <hi>ſet formes</hi> to bring with us, when we goe to prayer, that is, to God; Onely worthy <hi>Hild:</hi> as was ſayd, ſpeakes more for ſet formes than any we have met with, Mr <hi>Rogers</hi> himſelfe not excepted<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſo we take leave to examine the proofe he makes, theſe are his words, for we know there is much notice taken of them.</p>
                  <p>
                     <q>
                        <hi>I dare not Deny, but a weake Chriſtian</hi> (him we called by Scripture allowance a Babe in Chriſt) <hi>may uſe the helpe of a good prayer-booke:</hi>
                     </q> This is taken-up at a very cheap rate, without the price of a proofe; or if you will call it a proof, this it is; <hi>Better to pray in a Booke, than not to pray at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>This we take to be, as, we thinke, the Schollars phraſe it, <hi>Peti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tio principij,</hi> a mere begging of the Queſtion, It aſſerteth ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing, but proves nothing; It aſſerts this, That if a Babe in Chriſt, a truely converted one, have not a booke to pray by, he cannot pray at all, whence he inferr's, <hi>'tis better to pray in a booke, than not to pray at all.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Now we have aſſerted the Contrary, and doe aſſert it ſtill, That a Babe in Chriſt would pray to his Heavenly Father in the
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:117967:9"/> Name of Chriſt, though there were not a ſet forme of prayer in the world.</p>
                  <p>And we would humbly add what we conceive to be a truth, if there were as many ſet formes of prayers, that <hi>the world it ſel<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>e could not containe the bootes written thereof,</hi> yet all theſe, alltoge<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or apart, could not give the leaſt helpe to the Devotion of this <hi>Babe in Chriſt.</hi> All thoſe would not make him crie in prayer <hi>Abba Father.</hi> But this one Charge againſt himſelfe, which ſurely<note place="margin">2 Sam. 12. 13. Job 7. Luke 5. 18. Jere: 3. 13.</note> he can doe very readily, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> ſpoken from him <hi>freely, feelingly, humbly, ſincerely</hi> as <hi>David, Job,</hi> the Prodigall now <hi>come to himſelfe,</hi> and as the <hi>Babe</hi> in Chriſt can ſpeake it, is of more ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count with his God, and more prevailing to encline His eare, than all the Rhetoricke in the world, ſuggeſted to this <hi>Babe</hi> by ano<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers tongue or pen. <hi>Prayer,</hi> we have heard ſay, is the <hi>key</hi> that openeth all Gods Treaſuries; But now another's key, be it never ſo exactly made (to argue it by way of a ſimilitude) cannot fit the <hi>wards</hi> of <hi>my locke;</hi> Our plaine meaning is, and without a fi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gure; A forme of prayer, the exacteſt that ever was made, can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not ſurely fitt my needes, cannot ſpeake out the things, that I want, to the eares of my God; or ſpeake out His prayſes, for what I have received from Him. It cannot reach the troubles of my Soule, nor can it tell the Conſolation there; or ſuppoſe it could, It would not ſupplie me with the <hi>Spirit,</hi> By whome I muſt, through Chriſt, preſent all this before my God; for <hi>what man</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Cor. 2. 11, 12</note> 
                     <hi>knoweth the things of a man, ſave the Spirit of man within him?</hi> and ſo forth, for it requires our obſervation through-out. We will put a cloſe to this, when we have ſpoken two or three things more very briefly.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, We conceive that thoſe ſet formes cannot take any whit with a Babe in Chriſt, one Reaſon is, Becauſe ſet formes are ſo taking with us while we are out of Chriſt, we cleave to them as faſt as the skin to the fleſh, or the fleſh to the Bone; And what we cleave to, we plead for. Surely it is otherwayes with him or her, that is in Chriſt; as the nature is changed, ſo are the actions, the deſires, the affections. They remember well they never pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailed any thing by ſet formes; unleſſe to the <hi>hardening</hi> and <hi>braw<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ning</hi> of their owne hearts; The <hi>ſtupifying</hi> or <hi>deadning</hi> of their owne ſpirits; they never prevailed with God to give them a ſight
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:117967:10"/> of their ſinne, and forgiveneſſe of the ſame; for they were never in earneſt with Him about this matter; if they had, they had pleaded with their God in their owne words, and not in anothers for them.</p>
                  <p>It is the wicked man that ſticks to his formes as faſt as he cleaves to his ſinnes; The Babe in Chriſt not ſo; hee or ſhee is renewed in the ſpirit of their minde, and therefore ſtand as much againſt ſet formes, as the wicked ſtand for them.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, Suppoſe wee, for information ſake, That the per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon praying hath a ſenſe of the want of that he prayes for, That granted, we affirme, he hath no more need of a <hi>ſet forme,</hi> teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing him to pray, than an hungry man hath to pray for his bread; If he hath no ſenſe or feeling of what he prays for, which cannot be ſuppoſed in a <hi>Babe,</hi> then the ſet forme of prayer will doe him no good; for the forme of prayer is as dead a peice as the heart is, and two dead things, like two withered ſtickes, cannot enliven and quicken each other.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Wee would appeale to the Conſcience of every wick<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed man, <hi>ſeared</hi> though it may be, as well as to the obſervation and experience of all the godly that know them, and that are ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quainted with them; whether by their ſet formes or prayer bookes they have gained more ſtrength againſt ſin, or more ſtrength to ſin? To our ſeeming the anſwer muſt be (for ſo ſpeakes their con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation to the godly that doe obſerve it) by their ſet formes they have gained more ſtrength to ſin, thereby their hearts have riſen with more oppoſition againſt God, and indignation againſt the Godly; for it is a ruled caſe, <hi>They that ſticke faſteſt to formes of godlineſſe, are the greateſt enemies to the power thereof.</hi> And this is a knowne <hi>Maxime</hi> alſo, That a mans luſts are no more ſhaken by ſuch prayers, though he ſhould turne them over as faſt as that Antichriſtian doth his <hi>beades,</hi> than a Giant is ſhaken by the ſhak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of a ſtraw in a Pigmies hand.</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, A forme of prayer is an artificiall prayer made by the art and skill of another, and it is but like artificiall breath of <hi>bellowes,</hi> or the like, <hi>cold,</hi> whereas naturall breath is <hi>hot;</hi> ſurely cold praying hath cold working; and moves not at all with God; as good ask doubtingly as coldly, for, as the ſaying is, it teacheth God to deny.</p>
                  <pb n="17" facs="tcp:117967:10"/>
                  <p>Fifthly, Set formes of prayer are too pleaſing and ſutable to fleſh and bloud, to be pleaſing to God, or Good men or to doe the ſoule any Good. That which hath any virtue in it to doe the ſoule good, muſt hurt the fleſh, even to a torment; that muſt <hi>of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fend</hi> the fleſh that doth indeed <hi>defend</hi> the ſpirit. But this prayer by a prayer-booke doth no more execution upon our luſts, than a <hi>potgun</hi> can againſt an heard of Harts, or a Gun charged with pou<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der among Armed men. It is a <hi>lazie ſenſuall</hi> prayer, elſe <hi>fleſhly mindes</hi> would never ſo plead for it; for as was ſaid, <hi>Give them that which is ſweet, though it choakes them,</hi> Per fallacia bona itur ad vera mala, <hi>through ſeeming good and pleaſant things, wee haſten to reall evills:</hi> As per fallacia mala itur ad vera bona, <hi>through ſeeming evill things wee come to true and reall good things.</hi> It is but a ſeeming good to pleaſe the fleſh, and but a <hi>ſeeming</hi> evill to croſſe it, as the Babe in Chriſt doth, and <hi>wreſtleth</hi> with God in His ſtrength about it, knowing he oweth his fleſh nothing but <hi>mortification,</hi> ſave onely to make it ſerviceable to his God, and his owne ſoule.</p>
                  <p>Sixthly, Wee will cloſe with this; poſſibly a Babe in Chriſt may want convenient utterance, by reaſon of ſome defect in the tongue, or baſhfullneſſe in the preſence of others. And upon that account, our famous and excellent <hi>Perkins</hi> (but it was forty yeares agoe, when formes of prayer were of more account then now they are, and the hurt they did, not ſo looked into, as now it is, and with that allowance you muſt weigh them if they ſhould not hold waight) mooves in this <hi>Babes</hi> behalfe, for a <hi>prayer-booke,</hi> in theſe very words; <q>
                        <hi>The Grace and gift of prayer may be ſhewed in</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Ford. 480.</hi>
                        </note> 
                        <hi>reading of a prayer,</hi>
                     </q> 
                     <hi>other wayes it would goe very hard with them, that want convenient utterance.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee humbly crave leave to ſay, That notwithſtanding that want, which a Babe in Chriſt may have, there is no want of a prayer-booke though; This <hi>Babe</hi> ſerveth his God in his ſpirit, who can ſupply that want, yea a greater want than that, ſuppo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing he could not ſpeake one articulate or diſtinct word before his God, he can <hi>pray in his ſpirit</hi> through the mediation of His Son, and finde acceptance ſure enough; his Lord takes not his prayers by number, but by waight; nay, the Lord doth not ſo much weigh the words of prayer, no nor the grace of prayer by the <hi>ſcale,</hi> as he
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:117967:11"/> tryes both by the <hi>touchſtone;</hi> Hee not ſo much regards the <hi>num<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber</hi> as the <hi>truth</hi> of prayers, and theſe may be but breathings after God and Chriſt, yet they have a voice as loud in Gods eare as is thunder in ours.</p>
                  <p>Wee will draw to a cloſe; Who ever hath the <hi>ſpirit of Grace</hi> hath alſo the <hi>ſpirit of ſupplication, who may be in a groane, as well as in a prayer.</hi> Whence we may conclude, That he who hath this ſpirit, hath no need of a prayer-booke whereafter to pray. If you grant, he hath th' one in his heart, he will diſdaine, we thinke, to take the other into his hand. The Good Spirit is his Great Helper at this great and high ſervice, when he is engageing upon it. Take this withall, if pleaſe you, it pleaſeth this <hi>Babe</hi> very well,<note place="margin">Non actibus ſed finibus penſantu<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> officia.</note> for it makes much for his comfort; <q>That his Duties are weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed, and reckoned upon, not by their <hi>Acts,</hi> but by their ends.</q>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>WEE have humbly given our opinion, in way of ſatisfacti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on to thoſe two <hi>Queries,</hi> relating to prayer, under that Generall notion. And here wee have forborne to reply any thing to the cuſtomes and practiſes of primitive times, and times more lately by-paſt; for (firſt) They plead for formes of prayer in their publique places, wee plead againſt the uſe of them in our private Cloſets. (Secondly) Againe, wee are to walke cloſe up to the rule of Gods word, and not by the practiſe and precepts of men, whereunto ſomething hath been hinted before more than once. (thirdly) Wee have replyed nothing to <hi>Johns</hi> teaching his Diſciples to pray by giving them a forme of prayer to ſay, which is not ſo cleare to us, that ſo he did, but wee may ſpeake more to it hereafter.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="2" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. II.</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE come now to that ſpeciall prayer, which by good warrant wee call the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> and to make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer as wee can, and as the Lord ſhall aſſiſt to ſix <hi>Queries</hi> thereupon. But firſt wee may not diſſem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble what we finde written by worthy <hi>Hild:</hi> and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent <hi>Perkins, That the Lords prayer may be ſayd by us as wee
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:117967:11"/> read it;</hi> 
                  <q>Our bleſſed Saviour preſcribed to his Diſciples a forme of prayer, not onely to be to them and his whole Church a rule and ſampler, according to which all our prayers ſhould be fra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>med, as appeares. <hi>Mat. 6. 9. After this manner pray yee,</hi> but even for them, and to ſay, <hi>tying themſelves to the very words of it,</hi> as appeareth <hi>Luke 11. 2. When you pray ſay Our Father.</hi> So worthy <hi>Hild:</hi> excellent <hi>Perkins</hi> ſpeakes in theſe words; The Lords prayer is a direction and as it were a ſampler to teach us how and in what manner we ought to pray: None is to ima<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gine, That wee are bound to uſe theſe words onely and no o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thers, for the meaning of Chriſt is not to bind us to the words, but to the matter and to the manner, and to the like affections in prayer; And then a little after making anſwer to the third plea againſt the uſe of <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> Hee anſwers, <hi>That therefore the rather it ſhould be uſed as a prayer.</hi>
                  </q> But he makes no proofe hereof, <q>unleſſe this which followes may be taken for a full proofe; <hi>Sure it is that ancient and worthy Divines have r<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>
                        <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verenced it as a prayer</hi> chooſing rather to uſe the ſame words than any other, as <hi>Cyprian, Tertullian, Auguſtine,</hi> And ſo con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cludes, <hi>Wherefore this opinion that the Lords prayer is not to be uſed as a prayer, is full of ignorance and errour.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>THus wee have dealt faithfully in ſetting downe what we find pleaded for the ſaying of the Lords prayer. Yet we hope to acquit our ſelves of both theſe, <hi>Ignorance</hi> and <hi>Errour,</hi> in the words of truth and ſoberneſſe, though our Judgements bend from M<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>Hilds</hi> words. That our Saviour gave his Diſciples <hi>that prayer to ſay, tying themſelves to the very words:</hi> nor can we fall in with theſe ancient Divines, chooſing rather to uſe thoſe words in prayer than any other. Wee ſhall in all humility and modeſty interpoſe our judgement againſt this, without making the leaſt reflection upon the good knowledge, excellent learning and Godlineſſe of theſe two men, the one famous for all theſe all over this Nation, the other over all the Chriſtian world; And therefore how loath are wee to make mention of theſe things: But that here is a ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceſſitie for it, becauſe they that are ſuch ſticklers for formes of
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:117967:12"/> prayer, and are reſolved to bare themſelves up upon thoſe crut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ches. They alſo, who, as far can be obſerved, never uſed any o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther prayer but the Lords prayer, doe catch at ſuch ſayings as theſe, coming from ſuch excellent men, when they <hi>ſlightingly</hi> paſſe over what they may find in every page for their edification; wee were ſaying, full loath we are to meddle in theſe things, but for the reaſon above-ſaid; Though wee hope wee ſhall doe but our duty herein, which is to bring <hi>the ſayings of men to the ſayings of God; The words of men, to the words of God,</hi> as to their <hi>ſtandard</hi> or <hi>ſcale,</hi> where they muſt be weighed in the ballance of the Sanc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tuary.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>HEE is a perfect man that ſlips not with his tongue; and as perfect is hee, that ſlips not with his pen, <hi>Dabimus veniam petimuſ<expan>
                           <am>
                              <g ref="char:abque"/>
                           </am>
                           <ex>que</ex>
                        </expan> viciſſim,</hi> wee give and wee crave the ſame pardon. But ſtill wee take leave to doe our dutie, finding wee have ſuch war<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rant for it, to examine the forementioned words by the touch<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtone of Gods word. Thoſe brave and generous <hi>Bereans</hi> did ſhew<note place="margin">Act. 17. 11, 12</note> themſelves to be ſuch, by inquiring into, and queſtioning the A<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſtles words, who yet, if any in the world, might have been be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leeved upon his <hi>ipſe Dixit,</hi> his owne word for it, that Apoſtle might; It was enough that <hi>Paul</hi> ſayd it; no, not enough, for theſe truely wiſe <hi>Bereans;</hi> they have a ſure word to goe by, and to that word they will bring the Apoſtles words, to inquire of them whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther they be the words of truth, as wee doe inquire whether it be true gold by the <hi>touchſtone</hi> and <hi>fining pot;</hi> They that receive the word with all readineſſe of mind, will with the ſame readineſſe ſearch the Scriptures dayly, whether thoſe things be ſo or no. And behold a bleſſed effect of this; <hi>Many of them beleeved.</hi> Wee think this was ſpoken before, If ſo, ſo much the more wee ſhould obſerve it.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>BEfore we proceed to our next Chapter, we deſire the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der to obſerve for the cloſe of this; That theſe excellent men have but ſpoken their owne words, and given us their owne per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:117967:12"/> as to the matter of our enquiry, onely the later of them tells us the Judgement of others, <hi>Cyprian, Tertullian,</hi> and <hi>Augu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtine,</hi> theſe <hi>choſe rather to pray in theſe very words:</hi> But what is this to us, if we cannot underſtand our Lords words as they did? In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed we find <hi>Cyprian</hi> hath a whole Sermon of the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> which in order is his ſixt. And it was ſo cleare to him, <hi>All were to pray in thoſe very words;</hi> that he concludeth <hi>That to pray in any other words, argueth not onely ignorance but a ſin.</hi> Yet theſe are but words, ſpoken onely not weighed, and in darke times com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pared with ours. And, we think, there are ſome other words in the ſaid Sermon more to be taken notice of, which are theſe; <q>The New man, now borne againe, and like the Prodigall, <hi>come</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Homo novus re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>natus quando Deum, patrem dicimus, quaſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap> fil<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> Dei agere debemus, ut quo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>modo nobis pla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cemus de Deo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> patre ſic ſibi placeat &amp; ille de nobis.</note> 
                        <hi>to himſelfe,</hi> and returned to his Father, the firſt word he ſpeakes is <hi>Father.</hi> And now he is declared a Son, he carries himſelfe like a child. Whence he infers it ſhould be our great Care ſo to doe, That as it pleaſeth us well to Call <hi>God Father;</hi> ſo it may pleaſe Him as well to call and acknowledge us His children: which falls-in fully with what we reade, <hi>Jer: 3. 19. Thou ſhalt call Me my Father, and ſhalt not turne away from Me;</hi> that is as before explained, I will give thee the Diſpoſition of a childe, when I give thee leave to call <hi>Me Father.</hi>
                     </q> This now we have cited out of <hi>Cyprian,</hi> tendeth much, we think, both to our edifi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cation, and information, that we may know how to ballance his words, and, by the juſt weight we find in the later, make allow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ance for the lightneſſe of the former. And all this we ſhall be able to doe, we meane, we ſhall be edified and fully informed in theſe and all other matters neceſſary to ſalvation, when we ſhall humbly yeeld-up our ſelves into His Hands who leads into all Truth, and will not ſuffer us to be lead by our own humours or principles. So wee proceed according to our propoſed Method, to Anſwer ſome <hi>Queries</hi> about the <hi>Lords prayer,</hi> where theſe matters will fall-in in their due place and order.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="3" type="chapter">
               <pb n="22" facs="tcp:117967:13"/>
               <head>CHAP. III</head>
               <p>
                  <seg rend="decorInit">T</seg>He firſt <hi>Query</hi> is, <hi>Whether a wicked man may ſay the Lords Prayer.</hi> Now becauſe it is Queſtioned by ſome <hi>whether a wicked man ought to pray at all;</hi> Wee will cleare this firſt, <hi>That h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>w wicked ſoever the man be, yet he ought to pray;</hi> whereof that holy and learned Mans words, in the place forequoted upon the Title page, make full proofe; <q>Prayer, ſaith he, is a Naturall acknowledgement of God, That every man is everlaſtingly and indiſpenſably obliged unto by virtue of the Law of Creation, though the matter of it be<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> vari<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed according to the ſeverall ſtates and conditions whereinto we fall, or are brought. Every one, that lives in dependency on God, and hath his ſupplyes from Him, is by virtue of that de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pendance, obliged to this Dutie, as much as he is to own God for his God.</q> That excellent Expoſitor upon <hi>Job 22. p.</hi> 264. ſpeakes the ſame thing; <q>Wee owe prayer to God as His Crea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures, or in regard of our naturall dependance upon Him, much more as New Creatures, or in regard of our ſpirituall depen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dance upon Him.</q>
               </p>
               <p>And this might ſuffice; but becauſe we intend the inſtruction of the ſimple, ſuch as we our ſelves are, we intend to be larger here in ſhewing what the Dutie of every man is, how wicked ſoever, though he be wholy unable to performe that dutie. Firſt then</p>
               <p>We would ſhew whom we meane by the <hi>wicked man?</hi> Not eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man in the horrid ſtate of nature, lying in his blood; for there wee all were for as much as wee all were wicked: But that wicked man wee meane, who lyeth in his blood in his wickedneſſe (for our blood is as we thinke was ſaid, <hi>our wickedneſſe,</hi> as our Lords <hi>blood</hi> is our righteouſneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>) <hi>in that evill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> one,</hi> under the Dominion of<note place="margin">Math. 1. 23. 5. 2. Acts 26. 18. 1 John 5. 19.</note> an uncleane ſpirit within, and that other without, which rules in him, as he doth in the <hi>darkneſſe of the world, in the children of diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>obedience</hi> there. And hee is beſt content it ſhould be ſo, for in his blood he lyeth as on a pillow of Downe, or bed of Roſes, never better content than now that God hath made a <hi>puniſhment of his ſinne, giving him up to his owne hearts luſts,</hi> and laying him in the
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:117967:13"/> lap of his own will, to <hi>commit ſin with greedineſſe,</hi> as the hungry beaſt eateth it's meate, or the thirſty, ſwalloweth downe water, a very <hi>Epicure</hi> in both, <hi>paſt-feeling</hi> now, and <hi>voyd of judgement,</hi> pride hath ſo covered his eyes, and drawne ſuch a thicke skinne over his heart, that it makes him forget all God and all, <hi>Hee is not in all his thoughts;</hi> hee forgets all ſave himſelfe. And this his remembrance of himſelfe ſerves him onely to cloath and garniſh, feed and pamper that <hi>Idol</hi> his <hi>fleſh,</hi> and then to Glory in it when he hath ſo done; hee is out of Chriſt, and ſlighteth the meanes, the great Appointment of God, wherby to diſcover this his hor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rid condition unto man, and to deliver him out of it. Thoſe he hath ſlighted, turned his backe upon them, while he was ſitting under them, with full conſent of mind, withdrawing his heart from <hi>obedience,</hi> when, in ſhew, his eare <hi>gave audience; hating to be re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed;</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Zach. 7. 11. Pſal. 50. 16.</note> fully reſolved, as a man built-up upon the bottom of his confidence, that he will not forſake <hi>his way, nor his thoughts,</hi> nor<note place="margin">Jer. 2. 30.</note> will he returne unto the <hi>Lord;</hi> he hath no need of Him, being a Lord, and a God to himſelfe. <q>This is the wicked man (he is a legion) <hi>twice dead;</hi> the Goſpell hath been to him a ſavour of<note place="margin">Jud. 12.</note> death unto death; unto <hi>the death</hi> they are involved in, and are obnoxious to by nature, <hi>they adde a ſecond death,</hi> or rather ſeale<note place="margin">See Dr <hi>Owen</hi> pag. 356. Mr <hi>Caryl</hi> on <hi>Job</hi> 8. 19. 116. Dr <hi>K.</hi> Ch. 5. 63.</note> up their ſoules under the power, and miſery of the other, by contempt of the meanes of life, and recovery;</q> We will adde but this for the compleating of this mans miſery, out of Learned Dr <hi>Rainolds</hi> (and all this wee have ſaid in the deſcription of this man, and his miſery tends to this, that wee might heare and feare and not doe as he doth praeſumptiouſly, for) <q>theſe men, <hi>that</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Tre. with us, pag. 25.</note> 
                     <hi>doe their utmoſt</hi> to keep themſelves out of Chriſt, and by conſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quence under the curſe, as their perſons, ſo their poſſeſſions are under the ſame curſe; as their conſciences, ſo their eſtates are ſtill uncleane, <hi>they eat their meate like ſwine</hi> rowled up in the dirt of their owne ſin and of Gods curſe.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Notwithſtanding thus wicked though they are, and are reſolved ſo to be, yet <hi>pray they ought,</hi> though pray they cannot, but as a <hi>Dear roares,</hi> becauſe of ſome paine upon the fleſh; or as a <hi>dogge howles;</hi> or if there be no paine upon them, then they pray as a <hi>Parret</hi> ſpeakes: Yet, as wee were ſaying, <hi>pray they ought,</hi> though they <hi>be in praying,</hi> as <hi>they are in being,</hi> and their prayers are as
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:117967:14"/> their perſons are, an <hi>abomination</hi> to the <hi>Lord;</hi> for ſuch is Gods Law unto them; yet pray they ought, that is their duty, and the Homage they are to give unto the Lord, as was ſayd. The Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſell that <hi>Daniell</hi> gives to <hi>Nebuchadnezzar,</hi> Chap. 4. 27. and the direction <hi>Peter</hi> gives to <hi>Symon Magus,</hi> Acts 8. 22. cleares this unto us, that a wicked mans duty <hi>is to repent and pray,</hi> and doe the <hi>workes of righteouſneſſe,</hi> though he is no more able, of himſelfe to doe it, than a mountaine can moove and teare it ſelfe up by the roots and mount up into the Moone; or a bramble yeeld grapes; or a Thiſtle figgs; or a Serpent ſpit pearles; naturall impotency can give no excuſe to willfull neglect; <q>A wicked mans neceſſitie of ſinning, muſt not nullifie the Law of God, which requireth the doing of theſe things, though not with ſuch an uncleane heart as he doth them. The impotency of man muſt not eyther prejudice Gods authoritie, or Diminiſh his own dutie;</q> Theſe are the words of our Learned <hi>Rainolds</hi> in his Treat: <hi>pag,</hi> 246 247. where the Reader may meet with much more, giving reſolution to the ſame caſe with this, <hi>that a wicked man ought to pray,</hi> it is his dutie. And oh! that he could pray for a ſight of his ſinne, and ſence of that wrath, which he is treaſuring-up every day a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the day of wrath, being buſily imployed every houre of the day in damning himſelfe; that ſo he might looke after Him, whome the Father <hi>ſanctified</hi> and <hi>ſent</hi> into the world to be a pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pitiation<note place="margin">Joh. 6. 36. 1 Joh. 2. 2.</note> for the ſinnes thereof; and oh that he would pray againſt the Grand deluſion of his deſperately wicked heart, which will perſwade him to beleeve that he lookes after Chriſt Jeſus the Lord for <hi>life</hi> and <hi>immortalitie</hi> from Him, while yet he lookes not after the meanes, but turnes his backe upon the Glorious Goſpell, whereby He is declared to the world to be a <hi>Prince,</hi> and a <hi>Savi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>our,</hi> all ſalvation in Him, and <hi>none other</hi> Name <hi>given among Men</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Acts <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>under Heaven, whereby we might be ſaved;</hi> The deſperate heart of man will perſwade to turne the Back upon all this, The Goſpell of the Lord Jeſus Chriſt, and yet he ſhall have Salvation by Him, though not receiving His Word.</p>
               <p>To our ſeeming now this is fully proved, That a wicked Man ought to pray, though he doth not pray, neither can he, nor will he, unleſſe as <hi>Pharoah</hi> did, take away <hi>the plague,</hi> remove this e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vill of puniſhment. And then perhaps he will crie Lord, Lord,
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:117967:14"/> for poſſibly he ſees death, ſinne and judgement, not as formerly at a diſtance, but neare at hand, and upon him; and then with <hi>Balaam</hi> he may ſay, <hi>My God;</hi> And oh! that <hi>I may dye the death of the Righteous;</hi> Therefore he that liveth like a Devill would die like a Saint, and ſo he may pray at the houre of his death, when his time is gon, and the time of Gods patience is ſpent, and the houre of judgement is come, but then it will be too late, no re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>medie now but a Torment; He muſt live to God, that prayes to God, walke with Him, and before Him, who lookes for ſpeciall mercy from Him. For if we expect God ſhould come to us in wayes of mercy, we muſt attend upon Him in wayes of Dutie, dealing with us as Creatures endued with Reaſon, underſtanding, wills, affections. But becauſe all theſe are miſerably depraved, he deales with us as ſuch, and ſo depraved, wholy diſ-inabled in our ſelves for the uſeing or improving any the forementioned without ſpeciall Grace from Him, which He beſtowes upon us in the uſe of meanes He vouchſafeth to us. But though wicked men doe none of this, nor is it poſſible, as his eſtate now is, that he can doe it; nay it is the abhorring of his ſoule to doe it, for <hi>he abhorr's the Lord;</hi> yet he ought to doe it, That is the point, and we thinke cleared, he ought to pray, it is his dutie.</p>
            </div>
            <div n="4" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IV. <hi>Q.</hi> 1.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> I. <seg rend="decorInit">B</seg>Ut whether he may pray the <hi>Lords Prayer</hi> that is the Queſtion, which now we ſhall endeavour to put out of Queſtion, <hi>A wicked man ought not to ſay the Lords prayer;</hi> he is a proud, bold, and dareing perſon, he will adventure herein. It is probable he know's no other prayer, and this he received by <hi>Tradition</hi> from his Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents, who poſſible knew no other prayer neither. But he ought not to ſay this prayer, ſay we, and theſe are our Reaſons for ſo ſaying.</p>
               <p>Firſt, It is the Churches prayer, we meane not a Nationall Church, we have not a thought of it, when our thoughts are upon This Church, the <hi>Church of the living God;</hi> A Nationall Church a huge vaſt body, a Monſter rather; and as <hi>cold</hi> as <hi>froſt,</hi> which we
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:117967:15"/> know congregates, &amp; faſtneth together very <hi>heterogenious</hi> things, which <hi>heate</hi> ſeperates; we meane not that commonly called a Church, which takes-in very heterogenious perſons, wicked and righteous, the Beleiver and the Infidell, if not worſe; the <hi>Diſciple</hi> and the <hi>Drunkard;</hi> the True <hi>Saint</hi> and the Reall <hi>Devill</hi> together, for theſe were borne in a Church, and quickly after Baptized there, and growing up, though in their Debauchedneſſe<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> getting ſtrength therein<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as yeares come on; yet by virtue of their <hi>water Baptizement</hi> are become <hi>viſible Saints:</hi> we meane not theſe, nor that called a Church, a<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>d <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ath but a <hi>Name onely,</hi> till the <hi>Spirit</hi> within gives the thing; we meane a company of New Creatures, differing as much from the <hi>common</hi> or <hi>Nationall Church,</hi> as Men doe from Beaſts: That we may be cleare at this point, we meane the <hi>Generall Aſſembly, and Church of the firſt-Borne, The Sonnes and Daughters of God; begot and borne unto Him in Chriſt of wa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter and of the Spirit;</hi> It is their prayer; It is the <hi>Diſciples prayer,</hi> their's, who are diſciplined by the Goſpell, received, beleived, and obeyed; by their Lords appointment it is theirs. Both the Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tures (<hi>Math: 6. 9. Luke</hi> 11. 2.) we conceive holds it forth clearely, <hi>pray ye; And when ye pray, ſay.</hi> Our bleſſed Lord ſpake to His Diſciples, here is the <hi>mould</hi> wherein to caſt your prayers; this ſhall be to you a Rule and Sampler, according to the which all your prayers ſhall be framed; but of this hereafter. It is the Churches prayer, the <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>eleivers, the Diſciples, and Saints prayer really ſuch and indeed, which they can hold forth and have to ſhew for, not onely, becauſe they were borne in <hi>England</hi> and Baptized there (a meere vanitie, and leſſe if leſſe can be) but they were borne of God through Chriſt, by the Spirit with the Word, and ſo baptized with fire, and the Holy Ghoſt, it is their Prayer. It is true the wicked man claimes it for his, becauſe he was borne and Baptized in this Nation; ſo doth he <hi>Childrens<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Bread</hi> too, it belongs to him upon the ſame ſcore. But he hath right to nei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, as we have heard, and may yet more fully heare. Wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And humbly offer this to the thoughts of reaſona<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble men, can we thinke that our <hi>Bleſſed Lord</hi> would put theſe words into a wicked mans mouth? Bid him call God Father, Whome he knowes not, endeavours not to know, nay abhorr's
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:117967:15"/> to know? He indeed will ſay, for who ſo willfull as he, as <hi>Ba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laam</hi> did, <hi>My God,</hi> and as he, and he was many, <hi>My Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Num. 22. 18. Jer: 3. 4.</note> But who bad them ſay ſo? you know the ſaying; It is preſump<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in the higheſt degree to ſpeake of God, or from God, or to God, without His leave or command ſo to doe; You ſay, ſaith the Lord Chriſt of <hi>my Father,</hi> He is <hi>your Father, your God</hi> but ye<note place="margin">John 8 54, 55</note> ſay preſumptuouſly in ſo ſaying; He is not the <hi>Father of thoſe that know Him not,</hi> but as He is the Father <hi>of the raine; But ye have not knowne Him,</hi> ſaith the Lord. And not knowing Him, how care they, how they Rebell againſt Him? Can we thinke that the Son of God, while He <hi>tabernacled</hi> here on Earth, would bid notorious Rebells, rebelling againſt the light of their owne <hi>Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſciences</hi> within, and of the <hi>Word</hi> without to call God Father, and Him Lord, while they were ſpeaking and <hi>do<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing evill things, as they could?</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We humbly conceive, It cannot enter into the heart of a Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſonable man to thinke that ſo our Bleſſed Saviour would doe. He hath reſolved the Caſe; <hi>Thou ſhalt call Me my Father, and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Jer. 3. 1<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>.</note> 
                  <hi>ſhalt not turne away from Me.</hi> I will give thee the diſpoſition of a Child, or give thee to looke after it, before thou ſhalt, with my leave, <hi>call Me Father:</hi> I will put filliall-affections, awfull thoughts; conſtant Reſolutions into thy heart, to love feare and ſerve Me. And then thou ſhalt <hi>call Me Father.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thirdly, Yet againe, Can it enter into our thoughts, that our Bleſſed Saviour ſhould bid a wicked man <hi>call Jeſus accurſed?</hi> No; you will ſay, for who can thinke ſo? we doe, If we hold to this, That <hi>a ſenſuall man not having the Spirit, can call God Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Cor. 12. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>or Chriſt Lord: No man ſpeaking by the Spirt of God calleth Jeſus accurſed.</hi> 
                  <q>What, they ſay, that ſpeake by another Spirit, judge you, ſaith That Learned man; The Apoſtle would ſay,<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>Kendall,</hi> Chap. 16. pag. 145. Pſal: 110. 19, 20.</note> 
                     <hi>They call Jeſus accurſed. And no man can ſay</hi> (heartily) <hi>Jeſus is the Lord but by the Holy Ghoſt.</hi> Becauſe, as our Learned <hi>Rei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nolds</hi> ſaith, other Lords are preſent with ſenſuall, and wicked men, who doe with their owne eyes overſee, and by their owne viſible power order, and direct them in their ſervice. It is not poſſible, that they ſhould feare honour and ſerve Chriſt (which is to ſay heartily <hi>Jeſus is the Lord</hi>) unleſſe Chriſt be in them by His Spirit, and they in the faith. <hi>Senſuall men not having the
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:117967:16"/> Spirit</hi> may, out of externall conformitie to the Diſcipline and profeſſion under which they live, with their mouthes acknow<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge Him to be Lord, yet their hearts will never tremble and willingly ſubmit themſelves to His obedience; Their Conſcien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces will never ſet to its ſeale to the <hi>Spirituall power</hi> of Chriſt o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver the thoughts, deſires, and ſecrets (yet this is to call Him Lord) but by the over-ruling direction of the Holy Ghoſt; Therefore he blaſphemes in Calling God Father, and <hi>Chriſt ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>curſed:</hi> he hath no allowance from Chriſt ſo to doe, it were blaſphemy to thinke ſo; and that is our third Reaſon.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Fourthly, Nor would the Lord Chriſt put a lie into a man's mouth in bidding him, this ſenſuall man, we meane this <hi>Legion,</hi> call God, Father; when as He is not their Father, but they are <hi>of</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Joh. 8. 34. 44.</note> 
                  <hi>their Father the Devill, and doe that, which they have ſeene with their Father, even the Luſts of their Father they will doe.</hi> If it be asked how wicked men ſee the Devill doe, that which they did and doe? Worthy Mr <hi>Burgeſſe</hi> anſwers it; <q>Becauſe they expreſſe in their lives ſuch wickedneſſe, as was and is in the Devill, even the ſame things which the Devill would doe, and wee ſhould ſee him doe, if he were viſible before our eyes.</q> 
                  <hi>Naturae ſequi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tur ſemina quiſ<expan>
                        <am>
                           <g ref="char:abque"/>
                        </am>
                        <ex>que</ex>
                     </expan> ſua.</hi> As man's Nature is, and his principle with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in, ſuch are his actings and doeings without; <hi>As he is in being, ſuch he is in acting;</hi> If he be <hi>in the evill one,</hi> that is, under the power and dominion of an uncleane Spirit; moſt uncleane will his act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ings<note place="margin">Math. 1. 23. 5. 2. Joh. 1. 5.</note> be, for he will doe that which he hath ſeen his Father doe: Certainly the Lord will not bid ſuch an uncleane wretch call God Father; for that were for the Lord of truth to put a lie into a mans mouth, which were Blaſphemie to thinke.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Yet againe, though as Excellent <hi>Turkney</hi> hath it out of <hi>Morney</hi> firſt Chapter firſt words; <q>A man hath never leſſe<note place="margin">De veritate Religionis. Cap. 1. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> to ſay than when that,</q> which he is to prove or cleare is more certaine and manifeſt than his proofe. <hi>Omni luce clarius, omni interpretatione notius;</hi> Notwithſtanding we will proceed. The Lord Chriſt would not bid a man, (we ſhould tremble to ſpeake this, or to heare it, but ſith it is commonly done, and in a zeale for our God we would not have it ſo done being aſſured from a ſure word; That a wicked man Blaſphemes the Name of his God, and haſtneth his owne Curſe, by letting this prayer goe out of
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:117967:16"/> his mouth; as he doth by taking into his mouth the Bread and Wine at the Lords Table) wee were ſaying, The <hi>Lord Chriſt</hi> would not bid a man blaſpheme <hi>This Glorious &amp; fearefull Name, The Lord his God;</hi> and ſo haſten his Curſe, bringing upon him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe<note place="margin">Deut. 8.</note> ſwift deſtruction; but ſo he muſt that Bids a wicked man <hi>ſay</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Pet. 2. 1. Iſai. 52. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>the Lords Prayer;</hi> call God Father; <q>
                     <hi>My Name Continually eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day is blaſphemed?</hi> how ſo, or what had they done? why, they would <hi>lie,</hi> and <hi>ſteale,</hi> and <hi>ſweare,</hi> and yet would come un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to<note place="margin">Jer. 7.</note> Gods Temple, and call upon Him; They that did wickedly <hi>as they could,</hi> lyars, Curſers, oppoſers of what is Good (Theſe are worthy Mr <hi>Burgeſſe's</hi> words) Yet they will: come here and ſay <hi>our Father.</hi> Nay you cannot meete with any beaſtly<note place="margin">Jer. 3.</note> ſinner, but his heart is filled with this bold impudency, he will ſay as they did we are <hi>Jewes<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> i. e. <hi>true beleivers</hi> (for as that<note place="margin">Revel. 2 9. Mr <hi>Caryll.</hi> Job 11. 4. 21.</note> Learned man ſaith,</q> under the old Teſtament-Termes, Goſpell profeſſours are expreſt in the <hi>Revelations</hi>) I am ſuch a one, a true Chriſtian, for the time was, when I was Borne, and quickly after Baptized, and a viſible Saint I was ever ſince being a member of a (Nationall) Church, and yet this Beaſt-like man, doth not ſo much as <hi>pretend to pietie; which yet were double iniquitie;</hi> for the <hi>ſhew of his countenance doth witneſſe againſt him,</hi> he <hi>declares his ſin</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Iſai. 3.</note> 
                  <hi>as Sodom,</hi> he <hi>hideth it not;</hi> yet ſo impudent he is, he calls <hi>God, Father.</hi> And ſo goes on to the end of his prayer. Tell us your opinion here Sir, doth not this tread upon the brinks of Blaſphe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mie at leaſt? And if it doe ſo, It were blaſphemie to thinke, That our Saviour Chriſt would bid a wicked man ſay that prayer, for that were to bid him blaſpheme the Name of his God, <hi>fearefull and glorious.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Sixthly, And in the laſt place, to bid him ſay this prayer, were to bid him haſten his owne Curſe, and to bring upon <hi>himſelfe ſwift deſtruction,</hi> which he muſt needs doe continually, and dayly blaſpheming that holy and ſacred Name, which yet he takes into his mouth, and ſayes before the Lord and His people, <hi>Hallowed be Thy Name;</hi> As if a Malefactor ſhould ſet<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> himſelfe before his Judge, and remember the Judge of the Murther which he had committed, and call-down vengeance upon himſelfe: So doth e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very wicked man that calls God Father, and continues to rebell againſt Him; he minds God, as we may ſay, to inflict the Curſe
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:117967:17"/> upon him, which he hath deſerved, which certainly ſhall be done ſo ſoone, as he hath filled-up the Meaſure of his Blaſphemies: Wee leave it to your judgement, Sir; ſo you will rule it by the Scriptures, whether a wicked man doth not haſten his Curſe by letting this prayer goe out of his mouth? Whence have and ſtill doe iſſue forth ſo many vaine, lying, and deceitfull words, and Curſed Oaths, as he doth by takeing into his mouth the Bread and Wine at the Lords Table? We ſhall ſpeake more to this in the next Treatiſe where we ſhall hold-forth this undoubted ſigne of a faithfull Miniſter, whom Satans tongue (in his inſtruments and ſervants) is ſtill diſquieting, and as they poſſibly can, vexing and tormenting, becauſe the tongue of this good Miniſter is ſtill, and ſtill will be vexing and <hi>tormenting</hi> him and them: But if a<note place="margin">Rev. 11. 10.</note> Miniſters tongue will not <hi>torment</hi> Satan, Satans tongue will not torment him. There we ſhall alſo commend unto your reading, and, if you pleaſe, to your tranſlating <hi>Iſidor: Peluſiot's Epiſtle to his friend about this prayer,</hi> that ſo your Saint (that hath no more to plead for his Saint-ſhip, but that he was borne in ſinne, ſo he will acknowledge, onely he is cleanſed from it, and he hopes thorowly purged by Baptiſme quickly after he was borne, and can ſay this prayer before your face in the Congregation:) Wee were ſaying, That ſo your Saint may, by Gods bleſſing upon your inſtruction of him at that point, your ſelfe being better in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>formed about it firſt, may conſider, at what an high degree of blaſphemy he hath arrived, that dares ſay that prayer before his God, while his heart riſeth-up in Rebellion againſt Him.</p>
               <p>Here wee would add this, that the more excellent your prayer is, and this is excellency in the abſtract, the more unbecoming a loathſome perſon it is, as a <hi>pearle in a ſwines ſnout;</hi> But this is<note place="margin">Prov. 13. 5.</note> not the worſt, the more excellent and ſoveraigne a thing is, being received or uſed after the <hi>due manner,</hi> and according as God hath appointed it to be received or uſed, the more deadly it workes; the more diſtractive it is, the more it haſteneth the curſe upon the ſpirit, and bringeth-on deſtruction ſwiftly, being prophaned, and blaſphemed by uncleane lips, and hands; Wee might make in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance in the <hi>Word</hi> of God deſpiſed, and rejected; caſt behind the backe, it is a <hi>ſavour of death unto death;</hi> at once it kills twice, like the ſtrongeſt poyſon mixt with the ſtrongeſt wine, the very
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:117967:17"/> ſent kills, or as the wine received at the Lords Table by a viſible <hi>ſenſuall</hi> perſon <hi>not having the Spirit:</hi> See by their out-workes, what dreadfull workings the wine hath upon their ſpirits! But looke to the thing in hand, and here is a loathſome perſon, and delights in his loathſomeneſſe, which ſhould be loathſome to him, yet he ſayes the Lords prayer. Now obſerve him in his walke, his curſed act<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                     <desc>••</desc>
                  </gap>gs therein, and tell your ſelfe whether the curſe of God, which <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> hath been plucking downe upon himſelfe with <hi>both hands,</hi> 
                  <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap>: as with <hi>cart-ropes,</hi> doth not cleave as faſt to him as his heart cleaveth to his ſinne?</p>
               <p>Wee thinke wee have made ſufficient proofe, That a wicked man ought not to ſay this prayer, certainly he hath no warrant from our Lord and Saviour ſo to doe; But ſince hee will doe it on his owne head, as we ſay, and ſo is carried head-long towards his curſe, meeting it as it were halfe way; wee have read how hee curſeth himſelfe by calling Chriſt accurſed; and how he hath drawne upon himſelfe <hi>ſwift deſtruction;</hi> And wee have been the longer at this point, That all that ſee this man with his curſe up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on him, cloathed with it as with a Garment, eating his meat, as was ſayd, as a ſwine doth his, <hi>rolled up in dirt,</hi> may <hi>ſee and fly a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>way,</hi> as hee will doe, that <hi>heares, and feares,</hi> and will no more preſumptuouſly call God Father, as the wicked man doth, while, with a high hand, and an <hi>uncovered head,</hi> hee acteth <hi>villany</hi> a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt the Lord. Wee will cloſe this with worthy <hi>Mantons</hi> words; <hi>I have read of a Jewell,</hi> ſayth he, <hi>that being put into a</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Upon <hi>James 5. 16.</hi>
                  </note> 
                  <hi>dead mans mouth, looſeth all its efficacie; Prayer is ſuch a Jewell in a dead mans mouth, it is of no power nor efficacie, but to haſten his ruine and utter deſtruction.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="5" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. V. <hi>Q.</hi> 2.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> II. <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>EE come now to make enquiry into the ſe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cond Queſtion; <q>
                     <hi>Whether our Bleſſed Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viour gave his Diſciples this prayer, That they ſhould pray to His Father in thoſe very words?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>The Affirmative is much pleaded for, but generally, and uſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally,
<pb n="32" facs="tcp:117967:18"/> by thoſe, who are <hi>enemies to the Croſſe of Chriſt,</hi> adverſaries to all goodneſſe, and not acquainted at all what <hi>prayer in the Holy Ghoſt</hi> meaneth: Wee ſay it againe, becauſe wee would not be miſtaken, The Affirmative is generally and univerſally pleaded for by ſuch kinde of men, who cleave as faſt to their formes, as ſin cleaveth to them; or they to their ſin; And they beare them<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelves out at this point from theſe words of our Bleſſed Saviour; <hi>when ye pray ſay.</hi> But indeed it is not much to be minded what ſuch manner of perſons ſay, who will catch at any thing, that may make for their preſent eaſe, and put the <hi>fleſh to no c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſt.</hi> Yet it is to be regarded what any good man ſayth learned and godly. And thus, as wee have heard, worthy <hi>Hild:</hi> ſayes; <q>
                     <hi>Our Bleſſed Saviour praeſcribed to His Diſciples a forme of prayer, for them to ſay by, tying themſelves to the very words of it.</hi>
                  </q> Had he attempted the proofe of this aſſertion, perhaps he would have found it, a more difficult undertaking than barely to af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>firme it; ſo that excellent man ſpeakes upon a different account, whoſe words are ſo much in our hearts, that they muſt needs be much in our mouthes; we will tell our perſwaſion here, That a man ſhall not readily meet with ſuch like an expreſſion in any godly mans writings; and wee thought it our dutie to ſet it downe, that wee may <hi>wreſt</hi> it, what wee can, out of their hands, who are <hi>unlearned,</hi> and <hi>unſtable,</hi> and doe wreſt words, ſuch words as theſe, as they doe all other Scriptures, to <hi>their own deſtruction;</hi> ſo wee will now endeavour to evince the Negative; <q>That our bleſſed Saviour did not give this prayer to His Diſciples, that they ſhould pray this prayer, <hi>tying themſelves to the very words <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap> it:</hi>
                  </q> for indeed wee <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                     <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                  </gap> worthy <hi>Hilds:</hi> words to be the out<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>laſhing of his pen, ſtarting aſide, as the ableſt pen may doe, from its very ſcope, and maine intendment. <q>Which was to ſhew, That our bleſſed Saviour praeſcribed to His Diſciples a forme of prayer, which ſhould be to them and His whole Church a rule, and ſampler, according to which all our prayers ſhould be made:</q> Which is the ſame with learned <hi>Beza's</hi> latine note; for it is not in the Engliſh, <hi>Perfecta Chriſtianae precationis formula, &amp; <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                        <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                     </gap> typus,</hi> 
                  <q>
                     <hi>a moſt perfect forme of Chriſtian prayers, and the very type and mould, wherein to caſt all our prayers;</hi> 
                  </q> which words have no agreement with thoſe, that went before, <hi>not onely
<pb n="33" facs="tcp:117967:18"/> to be;</hi> nor with thoſe that follow, <hi>tying themſelves to the very words of it,</hi> very croſſe, as wee ſayd, are theſe latter words, to the good mans ſcope, and intendment: as they are to excellent <hi>Per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>kins</hi> words; <q>
                     <hi>The Lords prayer is, as it were, a direction, and ſam<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plar to teach us how, and in what manner wee ought to pray: None is to imagine, wee are bound to uſe theſe words, and none o<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther: For the meaning of Chriſt is not to bind us to the words, but to the matter and manner; and to the like affections in prayer.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Thus wee have heard what others ſay; now wee crave leave to caſt in our owne thoughts here, and to give our opinion; <q>That our bleſſed Saviour preſcribing this prayer, did not intend, That any one of His Diſciples ſhould pray unto the Father in theſe very words.</q>
               </p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>FOr firſt; The whole carriage of this prayer, from the <hi>Alpha</hi> to the <hi>Omega,</hi> from the beginning to the end, and cloſing words thereof, argueth it to be of generall concernment to the whole Church of God, more relating that way to the good of the Body, than to the peculiar good of any member thereof: though wee know this cannot be ſevered, the good of the whole, and of the part; for that, which is good for the Body, is good for the member too; and what is good for the member, is good for the whole Body; as what is good for the Bee-hive, is good for the Bee, and what is good for the Bee, is good for the Bee-hive; Yet wee conceive when a Diſciple comes before God, hee ſpreads before Him, his peculiar caſe, and ſaith, not <hi>our Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,</hi> but <hi>my Father;</hi> not others caſes, but his owne. This wee conceived relates to the Church in generall; but a Diſciples prayer relates to himſelfe in ſpeciall, and his owne concernments, though he can no more forget the Church of Chriſt, than he can <hi>to eat his bread, or his right hand forget its cunning.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>AGaine, our thoughts are, That the ſcope, and intendment, of this prayer, is mainly to be looked after, And tells the Diſciple what he is mainly to tend unto, and bend againſt, be his
<pb n="34" facs="tcp:117967:19"/> prayer long, or never ſo ſhort, <hi>Viz,</hi> 
                     <q>
                        <hi>The Hallowing the great and glorious Name of God,</hi> in the laying himſelfe out to the ut<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moſt for the advancement of the kingdome of Chriſt, in his owne heart, His intereſt there, and thorow the world; and the throwing downe the kingdome of ſin, and Satan there, and here and every where.</q> This wee conceive was our Lords maine ſcope in preſcribing His Diſciples this prayer; And this muſt be the Diſciples ſcope in the moulding their petitions thereafter.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>WEE cannot conceive that this prayer ſhould be put into the Diſciples mouthes to ſay it in thoſe words; and yet they never ſayd it ſo farre as wee can heare, not one of the Apo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtles, nor Diſciples in thoſe dayes, yet wee meete with many of their prayers: nor any of the Bleſſed Martyrs that wee read of, and we have read ſome volumnes of them.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>ANd laſtly, the height and depth, length and breadth of the Contents in this prayer, which wee thinke the underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of an Angell cannot comprehend, makes us beleive; That the Lord intended not, That His Diſciples ſhould huddle it-up as he reads it; Nor can we think, That any true Diſciple in the world, that ſhall well ponder on the matter, and weigh the contents thereof with all his heart and ſoule (which every true Diſciple doth not doe) will ſay <hi>that Prayer</hi> after the manner; <hi>Sing ye praiſes with underſtanding:</hi> ſo, put-up your petitions with <hi>under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding.</hi> It is good to be full of affection, but it is beſt to worke in the full <hi>Aſſurance of underſtanding.</hi> Affections without under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtanding, are blind; underſtanding without affection is lame; the want of eyther run's us upon a thouſand inconveniences. But if any dutie, then that of prayer calls-up all our Affections; It calls for a worke of the underſtanding alſo. Now, we thinke, no godly man's underſtanding (though his onely is opened, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>newed and ſanctified) is able to goe along with this manner of ſaying it, as he reads it; he will make a pauſe ſure at the ontrance<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     <pb n="35" facs="tcp:117967:19"/> 
                     <hi>My Father.</hi> We have told you our thoughts, as to this matter. Onely we entreat the Reader to obſerve what he met with in the firſt Chapter ſecond and third ſection, and in the ſecond Chapter, ſpecially the fourth paragraph there; together with the firſt para<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>graph in the Chapter following, which we thinke, refers much to that which precedeth, as to that which followes.</p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="6" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VI. <hi>Q.</hi> 3.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> III. <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether a Godly perſon he or ſhe, brings this prayer into the Cloſet with them, there and then humbling themſelves be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore their God.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We told you, we maintained the Nega<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tive, our Reaſons are.</p>
               <div n="1" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. I.</head>
                  <p>ANd the firſt we would onely offer to your Conſideration, being rejected by the godly Learned, yet we conceive no reaſon is given for their refuſing of it: <q>
                        <hi>That, which is a patterne to make all prayers by, ſhould not be uſed as a prayer.</hi>
                     </q> To this the onely Anſwer is; <q>
                        <hi>Therefore the rather it may be uſed as a prayer.</hi> But this makes no proofe, nor doe the words following. <hi>That ſure it is, Antient and worthy Divines have reverenced it, as a prayer, chooſing rather to uſe thoſe words than any other.</hi>
                     </q> And ſo many worthy Divines doe now, and yet by ſo doing prove no<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing to the purpoſe. We will offer but a word in it, and tell you what we conceive, that the Argument is very ſtrong; <hi>The pat<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terne to make all prayers by, is not to be uſed as a prayer,</hi> for if wee uſe the patterne for our prayer, wee ſhall never pray according<note place="margin">1 John 3. 2.</note> to the patterne; As the Diſciples doe not ſtint themſelves with any degree of holineſſe, Gods owne purity being their Copie, ſo neither can they ſtint themſelves in prayer, the Lords owne prayer being their patterne: We proceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>WEE thinke it cleane beſides the ſcope and intendment of our Bleſſed Saviour in giving His Diſciples this Prayer, if they ſhall plead their caſe with Him in thoſe very words;
<pb n="36" facs="tcp:117967:20"/> Now in this Caſe we cannot reach our Lord's mind, nor eye His ſcope, but by obſerving what He did while He tabernacled among men; He put up many prayers to His Father, and indeed, though Lord of all, yet as Mediator of His Church, and ſo a ſervant to His Father in the Churches behalfe, He could have nothing, nor<note place="margin">Pſal. 2. 8. Ma<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                           <desc>••</desc>
                        </gap>. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>6. 5<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. Heb. 7. 25.</note> hath He to this day, but He <hi>muſt aske for it:</hi> And among all theſe prayers we read not (and <hi>quod non ligitur, non creditur</hi>) That this ſacred prayer came-out of His ſacred lips any more than once. Nor have we obſerved it from the mouths of any of His Apoſtles, or other of His Deare Children Yet we read of their prayers, and though ſhort, yet were they moulded after <hi>this man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner,</hi> 
                     <q>That the throne of His Glory may be advanced in their Hearts; And that the world, and all that, which mightily op<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſeth the lifting-up of the ſame, may be throwne-downe, Cruſhed to the earth and ruined:</q> but never heard we this Prayer from their lips, nor from any of the Bleſſed Martyrs. Now, cer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tainly, theſe, being of the Number of That Virgin<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Company, fol<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>low their <hi>Leader</hi> and <hi>Commander,</hi> though <hi>haud paſſibus aequis,</hi> yet they follow Him, and did eye, marke, and behold His Bleſſed ſcope, and intendment in all He did or ſpake.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="3" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. III.</head>
                  <p>THe Diſciple doth not, as we thinke, bring this Prayer before His Lord for this were to limit and ſtint himſelfe, and ſo to <hi>Reſtraine prayer,</hi> which ſure was far from the Intent of our Lord to preſcribe ſo Contrary to the workings of His own Spirit in the hearts of His Choſen; Theſe find a reſtraint upon themſelves, as often as they find not the Bleſſed Spirit enlargeing of them to pray; and then humbled they are, when Comforted they cannot be: But it is far from them, as it was from the Mind of Chriſt preſcribing this prayer, to <hi>ſtint themſelves,</hi> ſo many words, and no more, as acceptable with their God, as ſo many <hi>Ave-Maries</hi> and <hi>Pater-noſters</hi> given out by Number, you know by whome. A <hi>naturall prayer</hi> put-up by the ſtrength of Nature, is a ſtinted and a limited prayer: But a <hi>Spirituall prayer,</hi> as a Diſciples pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is, hath alwayes an Infiniteneſſe in it; his ſpirit being right ſet, is enlarged to a kind of Infiniteneſſe in Gods Service; There is a
<pb n="37" facs="tcp:117967:20"/> 
                     <hi>Naturall Bias</hi> in his ſoule, which inclines him to a limited prayer; But we know the ſtrength of the Arme takes away that <hi>Bias:</hi> So the ſtrength of the Inward man takes away this <hi>Bias.</hi> Though this Diſciple is not able to doe what is actually infinite, yet his deſire is infinite in this, That being to deale with an <hi>Infinite God,</hi> were he able to doe ten thouſand times more than he doth, yet his heart would doe more. Oh that I could doe more; As he growes in grace, ſo his deſire after grace is enlarged, as much as a wicked man is after the world and ſin; he enlargeth his deſire <hi>as hell,</hi> and a godly man enlargeth his <hi>as Heaven.</hi> He limits not himſelfe; <hi>Thoſe deſires are boundleſſe which the Holy Spirit enlarg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth to a kinde of Infiniteneſſe, Cauſing thoſe to Center in the infinite Love of God unto them through Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> and this is our third Reaſon.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>THeſe Diſciples have their ſtated and ſet times for prayer eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry day. It is true, they pray <hi>Continually,</hi> or without <hi>Cea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 10. 2. 1 Theſ<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 5. 17.</note> Prayer never Ceaſeth to goe-forth, till the grace deſired comes-in: Though the words of prayer ceaſe in the mouth; yet the grace of prayer ceaſeth not in the heart: But they have their ſtated times for prayer, and the very <hi>flower</hi> and <hi>creame</hi> of time it ſhall be, which is appointed for that high Service: from hence we prove, That the Diſciple brings not this prayer before his God; He hath more to ſay, and muſt take more time for it, than is taken-up in repeating theſe words; They have many more words to utter before their God, we ſay not, than are contained in that prayer (for all the Angells in Heaven cannot readily tell us, and explaine to us the Contents thereof, or what is contained therein) but many more <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ords than <hi>numerically</hi> word for word are Contained therein; Therefore he muſt take time for it, and, if we may ſo ſay, the <hi>firſtling</hi> thereof; As he prayes to God con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tinually, ſo he praiſes God continually; <hi>prayers and praiſes goe together,</hi> very few breathings goe betwixt: but be they few or ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, the Diſciple takes time for it. No ſooner is he awake in the morning, but he aſcribeth to God the Glory, Who alone g<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ve him ſleepe, which all created ſtrength could not doe; and awak<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ned
<pb n="38" facs="tcp:117967:21"/> him out of ſleepe, elſe he had ſlept on till the Great Day of the Lord God had come: he praiſeth his God for this in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt. And no ſooner is he ſet upon his leggs, but he is upon his knees, praiſing Him with heart and voice, That ſet him on his leggs, whereas He might have laid him reſtleſſe upon his pillow, where many an head lyeth akeing. But how if he be awakned with paine and ſorrow upon the fleſh? (to take it-in by the way) Notwithſtanding he finds matter of praiſe, and his heart enlarged that way; He can <hi>ſing the high prayſes of his God,</hi> for thoſe glorious excellencies, that are in Himſelfe, and for the Emanations or flowings forth of the ſame by Jeſus Chriſt in the exceeding aboundant riches of His goodneſſe to His beloved ones in and through Him; and to himſelfe in ſpeciall; For though his fleſh feeles paines upon it, yet ſaith the Spirit, <hi>I am not ſicke, mine iniquitie is forgiven, my ſin is pardoned:</hi> Hitherto he never found, That his Heavenly Father did him any hurt by afflicting him, but good a great deale. Which may mind you of him <hi>Chry<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoſtome</hi> tells us off, <q>who was acquainted with greifes in his mea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſure, as his Lord and Maſter was (in His Churches ſtead, and for her ſake) that they may never have any hurt therefrom) and never came before his God, but the firſt words he ſpake, were praiſes to his God for his <hi>paines</hi> and <hi>ſorrows</hi> upon the fleſh (to uſe his own words) for <hi>his hell here,</hi> as well as for his <hi>Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven</hi> hereafter. And you may remember another, A very good Man, who enjoyed health, and wealth, all was proſperous with him for fiftie yeares together; and after the Date of thoſe yeares, he had ſcarce a Comfortable day to the houre of his death:</q> But this is for our Learning, how praiſe-full was he, That his God ſpared him ſo many good dayes, and inſtructed inſtructed him to that Diſcretion, as to make an improvement of them, therein to lay-up, as we ſay, for a rainy day, or ſpending time, and to beare his Croſſes, now they are come, willingly, and more, re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyceingly; for he found no loſſe by them. Indeed this is the Glorious Priviledge of Diſciples really and indeed ſuch; <hi>Amidst all their Croſſes they find not one Loſſe.</hi> But this is it we were proo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ving, There muſt be time for this <hi>praiſeing the Lord,</hi> and theſe muſt be uttered with a Man's own mouth; and ſurely theſe will not endure to be bounded within a ſett forme, nor can they have
<pb n="39" facs="tcp:117967:21"/> acceptance with their God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But that perſon, Man or Woman, who brings that Prayer before his God, Cannot praiſe Him for that he hath received (and what hath he, and hath not received?) for himſelfe, and for all his, for all which God muſt be praiſed. <q>
                        <hi>Prayer and thankes are like the Double motion of the Lungs</hi> (as<note place="margin">Dr. <hi>G:</hi> of pray<g ref="char:EOLunhyphen"/>er, <hi>pag. 61.</hi>
                        </note> ſaith that Learned, Holy Man) <hi>the Aire that is ſucked in by pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er, is breathed forth againe by thankes.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Nor can he pray unto Him for ſupply of what is wanting, keeping himſelfe to that forme of prayer, and ſpeaking to his God in theſe very words. The Diſciples of Chriſt are very wanting, at leaſt none knows their wants or ſees their wants, or feel's their wants, as theſe doe; And the<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> none pray's for the ſup<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply of their wants as theſe doe, theſe <hi>poore ones and needie ones:</hi> Indeed the Hebrew word for <hi>poore</hi> (as we have heard) ſprings from a roote ſignifying <hi>Deſire;</hi> And the Reaſon is, as one ſayth,<note place="margin">Mr. <hi>Caryl. Job 5. 15. 298.</hi>
                     </note> 
                     <q>becauſe <hi>poore men are commonly rich in deſires.</hi> They that are full of ſenſible wants, are full of earneſt wiſhes. And the Rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon why <hi>povertie of Spirit</hi> in our Spirituall Eſtate is pronounced a Bleſſing, is, becauſe the poore in Spirit are full of Deſires af<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ter Spirituall Riches. They are ever craveing and ſeeking to be filled with that fullneſſe which is in Jeſus Chriſt, <hi>with Grace for Grace;</hi> they would have the Image of every Grace in Chriſt engraven upon their Soules; or (in an holy Covetouſneſſe) they would be as rich in Grace, as Chriſt is;</q> Theſe are the words of that Excellent Man before cited; more there are and tend much as to give inſtruction, ſo to our ſcope and purpoſe, That a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ples prayer, whereby he makes knowne his Requeſts to God, cannot poſſibly be <hi>encircled</hi> or pent-up within that Compaſſe of ſix lines, which may be utternd in ſo many breathings, or within the ſpace of one Minut's time; for we thinke within that ſpace of time and leſſe, that prayer may be ſaid, or rather hudled; as with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>in two Minut's-time the 67<hi rend="sup">•h</hi> 
                     <hi>Pſalme</hi> may be ſaid over and over, whereby as you may remember <hi>Bellarmine</hi> could meaſure the huge body of the Sunne, and the quickneſſe of his race; <q>
                        <hi>For I obſerved</hi> (ſaid he) <hi>the firſt peering of the Sunne on our ſide of the Globe,</hi> and <hi>by that time I have ſaid that Pſalme over twice, the Sunne is up: and in a full body appeares to us:</hi>
                     </q> So then in twelve breathings the <hi>Pſalme</hi> is ſaid over, and over, and in ſix breathings
<pb n="40" facs="tcp:117967:22"/> the prayer is ſaid. And is not this to the heart of a wicked man, In leſſe than a minutes time, and that is the ſmalleſt parcell of time, he can begin and end his prayer, which being the Lords Prayer, he hath ſaid it as well as the beſt Clarke in the Nationall Church, and yet he prayed no more than that Pillar of Antichriſt, in his time, prayed, while he read over that Pſalme.</p>
                  <p>But to proceed in this a little farther; A Diſciples Prayer, wherein he himſelfe tells his whole <hi>mind to God,</hi> it is not uttered in ſix breathings: Certainly he hath much upon his ſpirit, when he comes before his God. We will put a queſtion here; and give you leave to Anſwer it. What would this Diſciple have more, than he hath, that he is ſtill begging? he hath all, God and all; he is <hi>compleate in Chriſt,</hi> and now what can he need? It is granted un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>to him, being one of the Number, to be arraied <hi>in fine linnen, cleane and white,</hi> which is the <hi>Righteouſneſſe of Saints:</hi> his <hi>Defence is the Munition of Rockes;</hi> The promiſe is made good unto him; <hi>Bread ſhall be given him, his waters ſhall ſhall be ſure;</hi> that is, he<note place="margin">Iſai <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>3. 16. <hi>Cal:</hi>
                     </note> ſhall want nothing for this life, nor for that which is to come; What would this man have more? You are, we hope, a Diſci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple, and not of the common Ranke or ſtamp of Diſciples, that have no more to ſhew for their Diſciple-ſhip, but that they were borne and Baptized in a Nationall Church. But you are <hi>borne againe</hi> and made a Diſciple indeed: And then you can make an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwer and tell us, what this Diſciple would have more, by what your ſelfe would have; he ſees his <hi>Lord</hi> in the ſhade, he would ſee him in the <hi>Sun-ſhine;</hi> he would ſtand more in the Sun-ſhine of Gods favour; That Sun-ſhine upon him never wearieth with its beame; The more it is, the more refreſhing it is; More of the light of thy countenance, more and more good Lord; Shew me Thy ſelfe more clearely: let me have a fuller ſight of Thee, and in-ſight into my ſelfe; for I would <hi>abhorre</hi> my ſelfe more, I would <hi>repent</hi> more. We verily beleive, That You, being a Diſciple, doe pray after that manner. And yet you find not a word of all this in the Lord's Prayer, we meane, explicit there, or expreſſed; Im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>plyed it is and much more in that one ſweet word, <hi>Father.</hi> We take leave to proceed yet farther, and ſo to trie your Diſciple<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhip.</p>
                  <p>You beleive on the Name of the Son of God; you know Him,
<pb n="41" facs="tcp:117967:22"/> 
                     <hi>who is eternall life;</hi> yet ſo ſure as you are a Diſciple, you goe on praying, That you may <hi>beleive on the Name of the Sonne of God.</hi>
                     <note place="margin">1 Joh 5. 13.</note> You doe beleive, and yet you would beleive; you doe beleive, and this ſhall ſave you from all evill; for as you know full well, and doe teach it your people, <q>
                        <hi>It is not this or that Degree of faith, which ſaveth,</hi> but <hi>the truth of faith, though but as the leaſt graine or loweſt degree thereof:</hi>
                     </q> Yet you reſt not here, nor will you ſuffer your people to reſt; for he that ſits downe at the loweſt degree of Grace, it may be doubted, he hath no grace at all, and ſhall become a Chriſtian indeed, when an Ape becomes a Man; or a<note place="margin">He that hath <hi>true grace</hi> may goe to heaven <hi>ce<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>tainly;</hi> but he who hath <hi>ſtrong Grace</hi> only goeth to Heaven com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fortably. Mr. <hi>Jen:</hi> on <hi>Jude pag. 165.</hi>
                     </note> Nominall Diſciple, becauſe Baptized in <hi>England,</hi> becomes a re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>all Saint. Grace is ſtill aſpiring higher and higher, ſo are you, being a gracious Man; you doe beleive, then we beleive, you would beleive more ſtrongly, that you might act more vigorouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly in the whole worſhip of your God; Specially in thoſe <hi>ſimple Duties,</hi> which none but the Diſciple performeth, fleſh and blood can doe nothing at them; as <hi>to love God; To Truſt him;</hi> To <hi>de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pend on him;</hi> To <hi>have joy and delight in Him;</hi> To have <hi>Commu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nion with Him;</hi> To <hi>take Him for your portion, and inheritance,</hi> and to <hi>be all in all to Him;</hi> Theſe are ſimple Duties, are acts of the ſoule, not compounded of matter and forme, And theſe you are able to doe through Him, that ſtrengthen's you: But this you<note place="margin">1 Joh. 5. 13.</note> could not doe, but that you are ſtill aſpiring after a full aſſurance of hope; And for this you bow your knee before your Heavenly Father day and night, for ſo true Diſciples uſe to doe; but then they bound not themſelves within the Lords Prayer.</p>
                  <p>More ſhould be added to this paragraph; but that we have been large in it. Sometimes this Diſciple looſeth the ſight of his God, A Child of Light and walkes in Darkneſſe of diſcomfiture and ſor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>row. And what ſayes he then to his God? Whome perhaps, his evidences being now ſo blurred and blotted, he cannot call Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther. There is a Cup of trembling in his hand, there are ſad ap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſions in his heart; what ſays he now to his God? No man can tell, but the Man in his Caſe; nor perhaps he neither; for he cannot tell himſelfe. He is in the ſame caſe his Lord and Maſter was in before him, and that is his Comfort, if he could ſee it; he ſhall be brought out of it anon with joy and gladneſſe: but this is his caſe at preſent, his ſoule is troubled, and <hi>what ſhall he ſay?</hi>
                     <note place="margin">John 12. 27.</note>
                     <pb n="42" facs="tcp:117967:23"/> We will caſt a vaile over this and paſſe on, <hi>Curae parvae loquuntur in<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>èntes ſtupent;</hi> but certainly he prayes, rather the Spirit within him; and no ſet forme in the world helps him with a word here, much leſſe with a groane, Once more and ſo to come to a period, or full ſtop here: This Diſciple now on his knees; as we ſuppoſe him to be, ſpreadeth the concernments of his Churches before his God, as neare and deare to him as his owne, he cannot <hi>keepe ſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lence</hi> being a faithfull Remembrancer: This takes up ſome time alſo, and more words, than are numbred up in ſix lines; and ſo much to our fourth Reaſon, why a true Diſciple brings not this prayer with him when he kneeles before his God. Before we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed we would make anſwer to that we have heard argued for the bringing the Lords Prayer before the Lord; It is this;</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Queſt.</hi> When a Diſciple hath but little time, and can ſpeake but few words, then he may draw-up all into a narrow roomth, and ſay the Lords Prayer onely, may he not?</p>
                  <p>
                     <hi>Anſw:</hi> To this we ſay firſt, That a Diſciple (Remember you ſtill<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> that we doe not meane a Diſciple at large, a member of the Nationall Church, becauſe he was Baptized therein; and received into that huge, we had almoſt ſaid, and let it goe, <hi>Monſtrous Bo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy,</hi> to whome Duty is a burden, and ſin light, with whome pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing time is <hi>waſte-time,</hi> that takes up more time than ſaying the Lords prayer, we doe not meane him, he is not in our thoughts, unleſſe it be to mourne over him, and your ſelfe, that account him ſuch, we meane a Diſciple indeed, and what we were ſaying of him, we are ſpeaking out) That a Diſciple indeed, prayeth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed, and being a man of much Grace, heares much, and reads much, meditates much, and <hi>prayes much:</hi> he is a man of much prayer; he ſpends much time to gett Grace, to make him rich to God, to get ſtrength in the inward man, to paſſe through all va<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rietie of afflictions; for all this he prayes unto his God, at the leaſt<note place="margin">Pſal. 55. 17. Dan. 6. 10.</note> twice a day, we verily beleive <hi>thrice,</hi> as others have done be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore him.</p>
                  <p>It may be ſaid, this ſpends much time; whereunto it may be an<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwered, That no time is better ſpent, than that, which is ſpent in Calling upon God, if called upon <hi>in truth.</hi> It hinders not in our <q>Buiſineſſe, though it ſeeme to hinder and though it takes (theſe are Excellent <hi>Preſton's</hi> words) ſo much from the heape, yet in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deed
<pb n="43" facs="tcp:117967:23"/> it increaſeth the heape;</q> The baiting of the horſe hinders not the journey; nor the oileing of the wheele, nor the whetting of the Sithe; though there be a ſtop in the worke for a time, yet as our Common ſaying is, <hi>A whet is no let;</hi> and praying time as it may be improved, is the moſt gaineing time. <q>
                        <hi>One houres Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>munion</hi>
                        <note place="margin">Dr. G.</note> 
                        <hi>with God may in a moment bring in more ſweetneſſe, than all other gaineings can doe to Eternity;</hi>
                     </q> The words of that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cellent Man Dr G: We would conclude, That a Diſciple holds on a Conſtant Courſe in prayer: He would rather forget to eate his bread, than forget to pray to Him, &amp; to praiſe Him for his bread. As he hath ſtated times for ea<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ing and drinking, ſo hath he for praying and praiſeing; and if he finds not a fit ſeaſon for eating, yet he will for praying He thinks much and often upon Glori<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ous <hi>Preſton's</hi> words: <q>The neglect of prayer uncovers the roofe as it were, and the Curſe is rained downe upon our Tables, upon our meate and drinke, upon all our endeavours, and all the en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>terprizes we take in hand: Thus with the outward man. And the loſſe we ſuffer in the inward man, upon the neglect of this Dutie is very great, that being ready ſtill to be diſtempered, to goe out of order, to contract hardneſſe and ſoile; for it falls out with a mans heart; as it doth with a garden, that is neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lected, it will quickly over-runne with weedes, if you looke not diligently to it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the way to looke to it, is Conſtancy in this Duty—there is much more to excellent purpoſe.</q>
                  </p>
                  <p>But (2) now ſuppoſe, ſome great buiſineſſe comes to hand (there is none greater than Prayer) and the Diſciple hath but a moments time to breath forth unto his God. What will he <hi>pray in prayer?</hi> we meane, what words will he uſe? Happily ſuch like words as theſe; <hi>Lord heare, Lord forgive, Cauſe the light of Thy Countenance to ſhine upon us; and take away that, which more than Eccl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>pſeth it from us;</hi> Truely We cannot tell what he will ſay, if you can tell, you may tell us. But we are verily perſwaded, he <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ill not ſay the Lords prayer, what ever his time be more or leſſe; And this is our Confidence in this matter. Now wee pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               </div>
               <div n="5" type="section">
                  <pb n="44" facs="tcp:117967:24"/>
                  <head>SECT. V.</head>
                  <p>WE ſuppoſe this will be granted, having its ground in the word of God, That ſo ſoone as a Child Calls God Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther,<note place="margin">Luke 15. 18.</note> and Chriſt Lord, he remembers he hath ſinned againſt Him; That is all we will ſay, <hi>he hath ſinned againſt Him;</hi> And now, <hi>what ſhall he doe?</hi> here is guilt Contracted, and filth too, who knowes how much? and now what ſhall he doe to have the Guilt remoo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, and his Conſcience pacified, his filth purged, and his Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience purified; what ſhall he doe? ſurely he hath no way to take, but to flie, as the Man-ſlayer, whome blood purſued to the <hi>Citie of Refuge,</hi> unto the <hi>fountaine opned for ſin and uncleanneſſe,</hi> and Entreate (for all comes-in at the doore of free Grace) that he may be put into the <hi>Jordan of Chriſt His Blood.</hi> Well, this ſhall be in good time, but not yet to his ſenſe and feeling (for we en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quire not what was done in Heaven before time was, but what is done on Earth, and within the heart, to make all ſure there) we were ſaying, he, having taken a right Courſe, and waiting at a ſure doore, he ſhall have a pardon ſealed to his Soule anon, in his Lords good time. But yet what ſhall he doe? for ſurely ſomething is to be done. <q>The Apoſtles (ſaid that Learned Expoſitour)<note place="margin">Upon <hi>Job 7. 20 p. 691.</hi>
                        </note> gave Goſpell Counſell, yet when men asked them, <hi>What ſhall we doe to be ſaved?</hi> they ſaid not, ye muſt doe nothing, God will ſave you by His free Grace;</q> No, they called them to <hi>repent</hi> and <hi>beleive every one of them.</hi> Sin muſt be knowne to be ſin (call it by the worſt name you can thinke of, then you call it <hi>Sin</hi>) above<note place="margin">Rom. 7.</note> meaſure ſinfull, and muſt be acknowledged ſo to be; <hi>Onely ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>knowledge thy iniquitie. Know the Plaegue of thine owne heart and</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Jer. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 13. 1 Kings <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>. 38.</note> 
                     <hi>mourne for thy ſinne,</hi> becauſe Committed againſt the Lord; and doe this as <hi>David</hi> for his Son <hi>every day,</hi> for every day thou ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſt;<note place="margin">1 Sam. 13. 37. Zach 12.</note> and as true Mourners doe, mourne bitterly; and mourne the more becauſe thou canſt not mourne enough. This is that the Lord will have the Diſciples doe. And ſo now, for we muſt Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tract, we will conclude; That Confeſſion of ſin is the great ingre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dient in prayer for pardon of ſin, whereunto the Scriptures ſpeake every where. Onely Acknowledge: <hi>Confeſſing their ſinnes;</hi> And <hi>forſaking of ſin</hi> muſt goe before pardon of Sin; yea and <hi>ſubduing</hi>
                     <pb n="45" facs="tcp:117967:24"/> of ſin too: All this in the ſtrength of God; but he muſt be <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quired</hi> of touching theſe matters; He will have ſin acknowledged; He will have ſin forſaken, put as far away by us, as the <hi>Eaſt</hi> is from the <hi>Weſt,</hi> as to our Love to it, likeing of it, deſire after it, delight in it: So far we muſt put it away, before the Lord will tell us, that He hath put our ſins ſo far away from Himſelfe and from<note place="margin">Pſal. 103.</note> us; That it ſhall be as poſſible for the Eaſt and Weſt to meet to<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gether, as for a Man and his ſin, to hurt him. So now wee con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>clude, That this Confeſſion of ſin, which every man will grant, muſt be with a man's owne mouth, not by any ſet forme what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, is not expreſſed, no not the leaſt ſound that way, in the Lords prayer, Therefore his <hi>Diſciples indeed,</hi> what ever your Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples<note place="margin">*</note> doe, bring not this Prayer before their God. And</p>
               </div>
               <div n="6" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. VI.</head>
                  <p>OUr ſixth reaſon, why a Diſciple bringeth not this Prayer be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his God, is, becauſe it is already wrought to his hand: he need not take any paines about it; The leaſt Child in his houſe, that can ſpeake, though he cannot read, can ſay it. This Diſciple, that knows in his meaſure, what a Diſproportion there is, betwixt the Great and Dreadfull God; and this worme, the Creature, (yea baſer than a worme, conſidered in himſelfe, becauſe a ſinfull Creature) or, to expreſſe it in excellent <hi>Greenhills</hi> words, <hi>betwixt Majeſtie and Nothingneſſe;</hi> And that <hi>ſloath</hi> to uſe the ſame man's words, is a Gulf betwixt this God who is all, and this Creature who is nothing at all, in himſelf conſidered, but a thing of nought, worſe than Nothing; This <hi>Diſciple</hi> now knowing all this in his meaſure, dareth not, as we ſuppoſe, and were ſaying, Come before his God with a prayer wrought to his hand, but having <hi>acceſſe to the Father,</hi> through the Mediation of the Sonne, <hi>by one Spirit,</hi> he caſteth himſelfe into the Armes of the Spirit, lookes for a ſupply from Him, enableing this Diſciple to put-up a prayer wrought<note place="margin">James 5. 16.</note> now in him, and wrought out from him by the ſame Spirit. This prayer <hi>wrought</hi> to our hands, The Lords Prayer, is the exacteſt peice of worke in ſight that ever was: But yet this Diſciple that ſaies this prayer (if any ſuch there be, as many ſuch there be in the Nationall Church) is not exact in this prayer; for praying
<pb n="46" facs="tcp:117967:25"/> this Prayer, wrought to his hand, he prayes nothing to purpoſe; Nothing wrought in him by the Spirit of God nor wrought-out from him by the ſame Spirit; he doth exerciſe neither the <hi>gift</hi> of prayer, nor the <hi>Grace</hi> of prayer. Nay, he doth not exerciſe any one facultie of his Soule in ſaying his prayer wrought to his hand, nor any one member of his body, unleſſe it be his tongue; and what is <hi>lip-labour</hi> before the Lord, any more than <hi>eye-ſervice</hi> be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> Sam. 24.</note> a Man? Certainly this Diſciple is of <hi>David's</hi> mind; <q>
                        <hi>I will not,</hi> ſaid he <hi>offer unto the Lord my God of that which ſhall c<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                              <desc>•</desc>
                           </gap>ſt me nothing.</hi> There is a <hi>body-prayer,</hi> of this we have been ſpeaking hitherto (to uſe that Excellent Expoſitours Diſtinction) which<note place="margin">Upon <hi>Job</hi> 11. 13 p. 108.</note> is never alone with a Diſciple, for woe to Body-prayer, when it is alone. And there is a <hi>Soule-prayer,</hi> which may be alone, and<note place="margin">1 Sam. 1. 13. Neh: 2. 4.</note> as fervent &amp; effectuall both as <hi>Hannah's</hi> and <hi>Nehemiah's</hi> pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers were; For the ſoule and ſpirit of a prayer, is the ſoule and ſpirit in the ſtrength of God lifted-up in prayer, which doth in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>finitely more in prayer than the body doth; yet in ſaying this prayer the body doth nothing, the ſoule leſſe. But this is the thing; A Diſciples Body-prayer (wherein he exerciſeth him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelfe every day, and likely thrice a day) exerciſeth the whole outward-man: The hands pray, knees pray, the eyes pray, (we have this in the place fore-mentioned) <hi>geſtures are ſpeaking in prayer.</hi>
                     </q> By theſe we pray when we hold our peace, and lift-up a loud voice, when we ſay never a word; but in ſaying this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er wrought to our hands, the Soule and Body both, every power of the one and every member of th' other may fit as ſtill as a ſtocke; onely let the tongue wagge, and by helpe thereof ſay the prayer notwithſtanding. The tongue is all-ſufficient for that worke; All the Reſt both the powers of the Soule, and members of the Body, may ſtand ſtock-ſtill the while; when one member is all-ſufficient for the worke what needs more? <hi>Fruſtrà ſit per plura.</hi> We had more reaſons to give why a Diſciple brings not this prayer before his God; but we thinke this may ſuffice; onely remember this, <hi>Fervent in ſpirit, ſerving the Lord.</hi> Wee come now to the fourth <hi>Querie.</hi>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="7" type="chapter">
               <pb n="47" facs="tcp:117967:25"/>
               <head>CHAP. VII. <hi>Q.</hi> 4.</head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> IV. <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether it be comely for a Godly Man, and true Miniſter of Chriſt to pray the Lords Prayer before his people, that is, to adde it unto the cloſe of his owne?</q>
               </p>
               <p>It hath been ſaid by two onely in our heareing; The one old enough to make a Miniſter if yeares would doe it. But—<hi>Tempora certè</hi>
               </p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Virtutem nec prima negant, nec ultima donant.</hi> The other young enough, to ſay no more: Theſe two, and one<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly theſe ſpake this, more than ever we heard ſpoken by any in the Cloſe of their prayers. <q>
                     <hi>Thou mayest Lord juſtly neglect our imperfect prayers if we ſhould neglect to ſay Thy moſt perfect prayer, Thou haſt preſcribed to us &amp; Commanded us to ſay.</hi>
                  </q> If this now can be proved, that our Bleſſed Saviour hath commanded His Miniſters to cloſe their prayers with His prayer, then The Queſtion is reſolved in the Affirmative, and put out of all Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, <q>
                     <hi>That every Godly Miniſter muſt cloſe his prayer with the Lord's prayer.</hi>
                  </q> Why? His Lord commands him: and he is not a godly Miniſter that doth not doe what his <hi>Lord Commands.</hi> But now we are perſwaded, theſe are but men's words, who are reſolved to ſay ſomething to carry forth their matters before the people, though they can prove nothing Nay we are Confident, That theſe two, <hi>the old Man,</hi> and the <hi>Novice,</hi> affirming, That their Lord commands them to joine His prayer to the end of their owne, have ſpoken Contrary to the mind and will of their Lord, and their <hi>preſumptuous words</hi> will be required at their hands. And herein we doe appeale to the Godly in all the world, Min<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters and people; And if any amongſt them all, ſhould affirme it, <hi>That the joyning of this prayer to the end of his owne is commanded him of his Lord,</hi> we would appeale from him, to our onely Lord God Himſelfe, the Lord of Glory. He hath commanded His Diſciples to pray; for they ſhall have nothing, as He Himſelfe the Mediatour and Advocate of His Church hath not of His Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, <hi>but by askeing,</hi> which was ſaid before. But if He hath com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded them to pray this very prayer, then we would humbly
<pb n="48" facs="tcp:117967:26"/> aske why ſhould they pray any other prayer? or why doe not they not give this the praecedency before any other prayer? this being given them under a ſpeciall command to pray; <hi>When ye pray ſay;</hi> as to our underſtanding they wreſt their Lords words, and thwart His ſcope and intendment wholy: more of this here<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>after.</p>
               <p>But we come to our undertakeing, which is to Maintaine the Negative: <q>That it is not comely for a Miniſter of Chriſt to joyne the Lords prayer to the end of his owne.</q> But firſt we would heare how they doe maintaine the Affirmative: <hi>That it is comely for a Miniſter ſo to doe;</hi> And what we have heard alledged for the Maintenance thereof, we will take leave to ſet downe in this place.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <q>
                     <hi>Godly Miniſters ſay that prayer at the end of their owne.</hi>
                  </q> We onely reply to that. So doe the ungodly and Brutiſh Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſters too, all over your Nationall Church; It is their very <hi>Sibbo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>leth.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">*</note> You may know a Brutiſh Paſtor, as by his walke, ſo alſo by<note place="margin">Judg. 12.</note> pronounceing of that prayer, we meane as to the words and ſylla<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bles there, theſe he can frame to pronounce aright, like a Clarke, as we ſay. But ſurely what theſe Brutiſh ones doe is not comely for the Godly to doe: Nor indeed can we poſſibly diſcerne their Godlineſſe, godly though they may be, and we hope are, by their ſo doing.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <q>
                     <hi>It hath been antiently ſo done, and cuſtomarily ſo now and of courſe.</hi>
                  </q> To this we Reply as followeth.</p>
               <p>All this makes nothing in the matters of God. <hi>Antiquitie</hi> (though Truth indeed be moſt Auncient) and <hi>Cuſtome,</hi> or <hi>mos populi;</hi> the Mode of the people, will plead as hard every whit for the greateſt plague of the world, for the <hi>head</hi> (that Man of Sin, <hi>merum ſcelus,</hi> as Learned <hi>Beza</hi>) of that Curſed Kingdome; For the Shoulders and pillars of the ſame, for all their Curſed doc<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>trines and practiſes; Antiquitie and Cuſtome will plead as hard for all theſe; And for a <hi>Service-Booke, will-worſhip</hi> too, which is as unpleaſing to God our Lord, as it would be to a Prince if we ſhould pay him money of our owne <hi>Coincing;</hi> for which he would be ſo farre from thanking us, That he would arraigne-us for Traitours. As a Miniſter muſt not ſpeake from God, but the <hi>preaching of God,</hi> even as it is written: So nor ought he to ſpeake to God, but by the Direction of the ſame Word.</p>
               <pb n="49" facs="tcp:117967:26"/>
               <p>
                  <hi>Queſt.</hi> But doth not this Caſt ſome blot upon the <hi>
                     <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>niverſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties manner and old Cuſtomes?</hi> for Generally the Learned and godly there did conclude their prayers with the Lords prayer; And it was ſo ſtrictly obſerved, That the Country-Miniſter who never uſed ſo to doe in his owne pulpit, yet going thither to take his Degree of Bach: or D<hi rend="sup">r</hi>: It was expected of him, he ſhould cloſe his prayer after the uſuall manner, and that he might not give offence to others, ſo he did, though with ſome offence to himſelfe.</p>
               <p>
                  <hi>Anſw.</hi> This we thinke cannot be denied, no more than can this, <hi>That from the Prophets in thoſe places, Corruption in Doctrine, as well as prophaneneſſe in life went forth into all the Land.</hi> But we beleive, That it is not now, as then it was; matters are done, we hope, at leaſt in deſire and endeavour in right order, and meaſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>red forth, according to the Standard of Gods Word: for it is true, we doubt not, which one ſaith of the preſent ſtate of the Univerſities; <q>
                     <hi>There have been more Muſes heretofore, but never ſo many Graces as now.</hi>
                  </q> But if not, which God forbid, yet <hi>non ad Conſuetudinem, ſed ad Norman vivimus.</hi> And as many as walke <hi>according to this Rule, peace be on them and mercy, and upon the Iſrael of God. This Rule,</hi> fixing the eye thereupon, and en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quiring not what was the <hi>Cuſtome</hi> of men to doe, but what was the <hi>mind</hi> of God that they ſhould doe.</p>
               <p>And this laſt ſaid may ſuffice in way of Anſwer to that ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly urged, and is thought ſo Cogent upon Miniſters, next to the pretended Command of Chriſt, to adde the Lords prayer to th' end of their own; <q>
                     <hi>That the Aſſembly of Divines in their Di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rectory for Worſhip, have thought fitting, Miniſters ſhould cloſe their prayer with the Lords Prayer.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>To that which hath been ſaid, we would adde but theſe two words (1) That we are inclined to thinke, That the fiery indig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nation of the Lord flaming forth againſt thoſe His enemies, who ſtood-up in their might for that old <hi>Directory for Worſhip,</hi> com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>monly called the <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> or <hi>Booke of Common-Prayers,</hi> and preſſed it upon Gods people with Arguments, <hi>Cogent</hi> enough, and too much with fleſh and blood. Whereupon it might, nay it was ſaid of that ſaid Booke, <hi>A bloody booke was that Service-booke unto them;</hi> and accordingly was it dealt with by the powers a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bove
<pb n="50" facs="tcp:117967:27"/> us, though not full-up to the rate of that bloody perſecuti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on was raiſed againſt the Godly Miniſters by the ſame. We were ſaying, we are inclined to thinke, That the <hi>Deſtruction from the Almighty</hi> is a <hi>terror</hi> to Godly Miniſters to apply themſelves to any other <hi>Directory</hi> for worſhip, than to the <hi>Spirit of God and of Glory;</hi> Who, being the great <hi>purchaſe</hi> of Chriſts blood, <hi>promiſe</hi> of the Father<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and <hi>prayer</hi> of the Son, is given to His Church for their A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſuffi<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ient guide, onely Help, and to make an A<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>undant ſupply unto them when they are ſetting themſelves in prayer to make their ſupplications unto their Father in Heaven. (2) The other word we would adde, is, That when the Miniſters of the Goſpel and <hi>Glory of Chriſt,</hi> who have their <hi>Miſſion, Commiſſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, Inſtitution,</hi> and <hi>Induction,</hi> chiefly and principally from Him, and can ſhew their <hi>Letters Patents</hi> for it, when theſe, are ſo hardly Driven, (as thoſe are, who are quite forfaken of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit of God) that they may uſe thoſe <hi>platformes of prayer</hi> there preſcribed, or elſe not <hi>pray at all,</hi> as we heard before, then they will, (for neceſſitie, they ſay, hath no law) be ſo bold or impu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dent rather, to uſe that <hi>prayer</hi> alſo, being the moſt exact forme of all formes. But theſe never were, and never ſhall be ſo for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſaken of their God; And in aſſured Confidence thereof we pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceed.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <q>This we have heard, ſome one of us at leaſt, alled<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ged for the ſaying of this prayer. There is a <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> upon all the faculties of the ſoule. And the memory amidſt the Reſt is a very ſickly, weake, and infirme thing; So as we many-times forget to put up thoſe Requeſts unto God, which were in the purpoſe of our hearts to doe. Now to helpe and ſuccour us in this matter, we adjoine the Lords prayer to the end of ours, that being compleat as we all know, in the whole and in every part, and Containes in it, as the Creed, all things to be beleived, ſo this, all things to be deſired.</q> To this we reply.</p>
               <p>Granting this firſt, That this <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> is <hi>Epidemicall,</hi> univerſal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly ſpread over all men, and over all in man. And the Memory, <hi>the Soule's ſtore-houſe</hi> is fearefully tainted with it, moſt unhappily, and tenaciouſly retentive of all that is evill; So as what was but once heard, ſeene or done, giving pleaſure to the fleſh, will be kept in the Memory and repeated there, who knowes how long
<pb n="51" facs="tcp:117967:27"/> and how often? (yet take-it-in by the way, as often as any evill, ſeene heard or done is remembred with delight, ſo often is it act<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed over againe) But now when any thing truely Good is Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mended to it, and received-in, of how ſhort continuance it is there? If a <hi>Hand Allmighty</hi> lodgeth it not there, and keepeth it there! The memory of it ſelfe, and in it's owne nature is a very Step-dame to Good or like a very leaking veſſell. This is her Sickneſſe, and if it be not Cured, it will be our woe. And now to draw nearer to the point in hand, we cannot poſſibly ſee<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> though, we hope, we Crie for His <hi>eye-ſalve,</hi> which onely maketh to ſee; how the <hi>ſickneſſe</hi> of the memory, cauſing the praying man to for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>get what he would have remembred, and made his requeſt to God for, Can be helped (for to this particular we ſpeake) by <hi>ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joining His Lords prayer.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>We crave leave to aske this Godly Miniſter, what he hath for<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>got to petition his God in behalfe of the people, to whome he is made an <hi>Over-ſeer.</hi> He hath not Confeſſed their ſinnes ſo fully nor ſo feelingly as he ſhould, and thought to have done; This may be; He knew full well ſome ſpeciall mercies his people had received from God, and he quite forgot to render God the praiſe; He knew as well ſome ſpeciall mercies his people had not and yet felt not any want of them, as a <hi>ſeeing eye,</hi> and <hi>heareing eare,</hi> but he quite forgot here alſo. He was well acquainted with ſome par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular miſery, that was felt by ſome one or more of his people, being ſickneſſe and ſorrow upon the fleſh: and another miſery he might know of alſo, which is the <hi>miſery of all miſeries,</hi> becauſe not <hi>felt</hi> nor <hi>feared,</hi> yet clapt faſt upon them, <hi>perverſneſſe of Spirit,</hi> and <hi>hardneſſe of heart.</hi> Here the Godly man's memory may fal<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>e him alſo. In all theſe, he might not petition God as he ought and haply thought to have done, and in ſome of theſe perticulars his memory wholy failed him. Now he will rele<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ve himſelfe and his people, whoſe good he ſpecially intends, by <hi>ſaying the Lords prayer.</hi> But is that the way to releive himſelfe or them? We hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly offer it to the thoughts of every intelligent Man. Will his re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peating the Lords prayer before the people help them, when they are returned home, to Confeſſe their ſin there more fully or fee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly? doth that prayer ſupply them with words that way? or to praiſe God for the mercies they have, or to pray unto Him for
<pb n="52" facs="tcp:117967:28"/> what they would have; for the takeing away the Stone in the heart, if it be not all over Stone, as deſirerouſly as we would have the Stone taken-out of the Bladder; but is there one expreſſe<note place="margin">*</note> word in the Lords prayer that helpes to the putting-up that great petition? wee meddle not with what is Comprehended there (which exceeds the Comprehenſion of an Angell) but with what is <hi>expreſſed</hi> there: And to our ſeeming there is not in that prayer, one expreſſe word there, that can helpe the praying man in all or any of thoſe perticulars before-mentioned.</p>
               <p>To cloſe this we conceive it to be thus; every godly perſon going to prayer, goes to God in the Name of Jeſus Chriſt; <hi>Through Him by the Spirit, he hath an acceſſe unto the Father.</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 2.</note> And oh what a deale of Eloquence and Rhetorick is in this one word, <hi>Father!</hi> how it works upon the bowells of the Father, upon the bowells of the Child too! ſo as the Child cannot chuſe but crave, the Father cannot chuſe but grant, what ever is good for the Child. There is a reciprocall worke ſtill, a reflexing Act of the ſoule. The Father's bowells yerne towards the Child, The Child's bowells yerne towards the Father. But we recall our ſelves, being to deliver our thoughts what a Godly Miniſter doth, when he hath entred the pulpit. Surely in deſire and endeavour he comes wholy off from himſelfe; he uſeth all that Ged hath given him, and layeth out the very <hi>Male of his flocke,</hi> for that very end given him: but he truſteth it not, he hath no <hi>Confi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence in the fleſh:</hi> It is fully and wholy ſet upon his God; <hi>He loves to be truſted, and cannot be truſted too much; as the creature cannot be truſted too little.</hi> In a word, he rolles himſelfe upon <hi>God,</hi> putts himſelfe as he can, into the good <hi>Spirits hand;</hi> Leaves his matters there, humblie expects ſupplies from Him; He is in the place, where he ſhould be, unto which his God hath called him; upon his worke, which he doth with more Delight than to receive his wages. Now he would not doubt but that the good Spirit to Whome he hath committed himſelfe and his worke, will carry him through it both in praying and preaching. And now, for now we are cloſeing the point, notwithſtanding the ſickneſſe of his memory, and many other his infirmities, who knowes how many? yet <hi>he knowes Whome he hath truſted,</hi> and upon Whoſe ſcore, and that He is able to leade him unto his worke, and to carry him
<pb n="53" facs="tcp:117967:28"/> through his worke<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> nor dares he for his life take a dead letter<note place="margin">*</note> (ſuch a thing is the Lords prayer, as uttered by Man, as dead as other letters he reades in the ſame Chapter) he will not, we were ſaying take a dead letter to helpe the living Spirit. Theſe are our thoughts of this matter.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <q>We have heard in the Laſt place, this alledged for the ſaying the Lord's prayer at the end of their owne prayer; our prayers are very imperfect, we all know, and God may neg<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lect them; therefore wee adde the Lords prayer to the end of our's, that perfect and compleate prayer which the Father will not neglect.</q>
               </p>
               <p>We replie, Granting as before, that the prayers of the beſt men are but imperfect, as themſelves are, very imperfect things. Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er is a mixed or Compounded Dutie, for though it be wrought within by the Spirit of God, before it be put-out by the tongue, yet fleſh hath much to doe in it, enough to defile it; and ſo the beſt prayer formed as we heard, paſſeth from us, as Wine through a Dunghill, therefore theſe can have no acceptance for the pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers ſake, nor for his ſake that prayeth: if that be all which makes for its acceptance, it will be neglected ſure enough; but for His ſake onely, Whoſe buiſineſſe it is now in heaven to <hi>take away the</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Revel. 5.</note> 
                  <hi>iniquity of our holy things,</hi> and <hi>to preſent our perſons and our ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vices pure and ſpotleſſe in His ſight;</hi> And, in ſpeciall, theſe pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers as the ſweeteſt <hi>odours</hi> in the Noſtrills of His Father; provided ſtill, that we loath this uncleanneſſe, that cleaves ſo faſt to our perſons and prayers, and put it away as a loathed thing; Now it ſhall doe us no hurt, nor hinder our prayers neither; for it is not <hi>what Corruption cleaves to us, but whether we cleave to it; not the having of it;</hi> for <hi>as ſure</hi> we have it, as it is ſure we have fleſh: <hi>but it is the Loveing of it. No more ſin is imputed by God, than is ſeene and allowed by us.</hi> So then it is granted, That Prayers are very imperfect, they receive a tincture of uncleanneſſe, which cleaves to the ſpirit and mind of a man, though renewed, that are ſubſervient and inſtrumentall in this praying worke; they are <hi>ſim<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple duties,</hi> that are ſo good, that none but the good can doe them, and they cannot doe them ill, we meane, not <hi>ſinfully,</hi> though <hi>im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perfectly,</hi> as to <hi>love God,</hi> to <hi>feare</hi> Him, to <hi>truſt</hi> Him, to <hi>rejoyce,</hi> yea to glory in Him, having choſen Him for their portion, and ſet their hearts upon Him.</p>
               <pb n="54" facs="tcp:117967:29"/>
               <p>To put a cloſe to this alſo. Will the adding that perfect pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er to the end of yours, make any thing at all towards the takeing away the uncleanneſſe of your prayers? or helpe at all againſt the imperfection thereof? We take it, you muſt anſwer one way or other; It helps, or it doth not helpe: if you ſay it helpeth, how abſurd were your ſaying? you know, <hi>Who liveth ever</hi> to helpe at this worke, and <hi>all proud helpers together with Him ſhall ſtoop un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der Him;</hi> If you ſay the adding the Lords prayer to the end of yours, helpeth not, no, not at all, then you ſay all the Truth as to this matter; but withall we feare, you charge your ſelves with ſome folly, in adding that to your prayers, which profiteth not at all, being never intended for that end. We will conclude with this, It profiteth no more than doth dead fleſh profit a quickned and quicking ſpirit: So we come to make out the <hi>Negative, That it is not comely for a Godly Miniſter to adde the Lords prayer to the end of his owne.</hi>
               </p>
               <div n="2" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. II.</head>
                  <p>OUr Reaſons are theſe; Firſt, Their Lord commands them not ſo to doe; for if ſo, an abſurditie would follow; If their Lord hath commanded them ſo to doe, then <hi>ſ<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>li &amp; ſemper,</hi> this is the onely <hi>prayer</hi> they muſt ſay, and alwayes ſay; for the Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand<note place="margin">
                        <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 word">
                           <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
                        </gap>
                     </note> of Chriſt muſt take place ſtill. It is this prayer and no other, and not at this time onely, but at all times, <hi>When ye pray ſay.</hi> Thus we conceive it muſt be, and this were very abſurd and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>congruous to common ſenſe and reaſon. The Commands of God in the old Teſtament, as to the Sacraments there, and other legall obſervations of places and of Dayes, they had their <hi>untill: untill the fullneſſe of time ſhall come,</hi> untill God be manifeſted in the fleſh, for theſe pointed unto Him, <hi>That was to come;</hi> 
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>t the Commands of Chriſt now, as we conceive, bind us to their obſervation till His Comming in ſome glorious way, whether to reſtore His Church, <hi>Math: 17. 11. Acts</hi> 3. 21. or make her compleate in Glory, is too deepe for our ſhallowneſſe; But His commands bind us <hi>till</hi> His Comeing. Nothing ſhall be added to them or taken from them. See <hi>Hild:</hi> on <hi>Joh: 4. pag:</hi> 187.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, If their Lord commands them to ſay this prayer at
<pb n="55" facs="tcp:117967:29"/> the end of their owne, then the Godly Miniſters all over the Land, truely and indeed ſuch, could have no more omitted the ſaying of it, than they could forbeare to eate and drinke: for the Commands of Chriſt, all and every one doe come with as much force upon their Spirits, to doe thereafter, as Eating and drinking come upon them when their need is. For they have the ſame mind that is in Chriſt, they <hi>delight to doe His will,</hi> His Command, His <hi>Law is within their heart,</hi> the doing of it is their meat and drinke, (ſo ſaith the Spirit) now what an abſurd thing were this, for can it take with a Reaſonable man; That theſe words, <hi>when ye pray ſay</hi> (this prayer at the end of you<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s) <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>or <hi>have not I commanded you?</hi> have they not My Stamp upon them? And yet ſcarce one Godly Miniſter among many doe or dare ſay it at the end of their owne. Certainly they would doe the Command of their Lord, boldly and conſtantly, and fervently too; though it ſhould put them to as much <hi>coſt</hi> the doeing of it, as is imaginable, yet they would doe it, <hi>Their Lord hath commanded it.</hi> This is the poin<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>, The Godly Min<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ſter would doe it, he could not but doe it, were it commanded him of his Lord, <hi>when ye pray ſay.</hi> And it were ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurd to ſay or thinke the Contrary.</p>
                  <p>And which we muſt not forget, It were as abſurd to thinke, that any one Brutiſh Paſtour, amidſt the <hi>Droves</hi> and <hi>Herds</hi> of them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ould ſay this prayer, ſuppoſe now, what they pretend<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> our <hi>Lord Commanded them</hi> ſo to ſay, <hi>when ye pray ſay;</hi> this pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er after your owne, for it hath My ſtamp of Command upon it, ſuppoſe it ſo to be, as they ſay, Then it were abſurd to thinke, they would ſay, as now they doe willingly and more, rejoyceing<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly, it being commanded them of God; for all the Commands of God, as was ſaid before, are an abomination to them: they ab<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>horre<note place="margin">Chriſtmas day. pag. 18, 19.</note> to doe them, as they <hi>Abhorre God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> their heart ſtands in the greateſt oppoſition to the Commands of Chriſt; as doe the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moteſt extreames, Heaven and Hell. Theſe doe wickedly as they can, and cannot but doe it, <hi>fullfilling all the wills of the fleſh,</hi> and ſo they will doe, that's the <hi>voice of their nature;</hi> The Godly Man doth <hi>fooliſhly</hi> ſometimes, we meane <hi>ſinfully</hi> againſt the commands of his Lord, but not with full conſent of his will, he doth it<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> over<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taken now, or ſurprized, or betrayed, but, <hi>oh! he would not doe it,</hi> that is <hi>the voice of Grace.</hi> The evill man in doeing God's com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands,
<pb n="56" facs="tcp:117967:30"/> is as the good man in doeing the commands of the fleſh. The evill man does doe God's Commands ſometimes, he reades, and heares, and prayes, but as unwillingly all this, as <hi>Haman</hi> brought <hi>Mordecai</hi> on horſebacke through the ſtreets of the Ci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie, <hi>that he would not doe in good things, that doth he.</hi> The godly man ſometimes doth the Commands of the fleſh, which are moſt contrary to the Commands of Chriſt, but <hi>what He hates</hi> that <hi>doth he.</hi> This is the point, and ſo we have done, A Brutiſh Paſtour, and a brutiſh people are ſo farre from doeing the Commands of Chriſt, That they <hi>hate</hi> to doe it, <hi>with their whole heart, and with their whole ſoule;</hi> and it were abſurd to ſay or thinke the contra<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry. <hi>When ye pray, ſay</hi> (this prayer after your owne) The Lord Chriſt commands no ſuch thing, neither ever came it in His heart, for could we ſuppoſe, our Lord had commanded ſo to doe, The Paſtour <hi>after Gods owne heart</hi> had never omitted it; The Brutiſh one had never ſaid it, unleſſe as a Parret his <hi>chaire,</hi> he had not ſaid it like a Clarke, as now he ſayes it, nor done it ſo, as he doth the wills of the fleſh. This is the ſecond.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, We would aske this Godly Miniſter, what good he finds by adding this prayer to the end of his own, which we would ſuppoſe was <hi>wrought</hi> in him, and out from him, by the Spirit of God. We know <hi>Cui bono?</hi> is the greateſt enquiry; and in this Caſe, what Spirituall advantage by ſo doing? what hath this ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vantaged the Spirit; God's Spirit, or his owne, renewed by the ſame Spirit? We paſſe this, leaving it upon his thoughts, having ſpoken ſo much thereunto before; onely this we would adde; It is, you know, a ſure ſaying, <hi>That every act of Grace, extends grace in the heart of a Diſciple; as every act of ſin, extends ſin in the ſinner; for grace,</hi> as corruption, gaines by acting; Now it is left upon your thoughts, whether you have found grace hath been extended in your heart, by the addition of this prayer to the end of your owne?</p>
                  <p>Fourthly, What good doth he doe by repeating this prayer, or what advantage is it to his hearers? Certainly a Godly Mini<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter ſhould looke to that, whereby he may <hi>profit his people. The Preacher was wiſe;</hi> and how did he evidence his wiſdome? <hi>He</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Eccleſ. 12. 9.</note> 
                     <hi>ſtill taught the people knowledge, yea he gave good heed, and ſought out:</hi> he would not ſpeake a word ſure but to profit, and the build<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="57" facs="tcp:117967:30"/> up of his people. Two great workes he is continually verſed and exerciſed in, being charged upon him, <hi>praying and preaching,</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 6. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap>.</note> and how ſtudiouſly carefull is he, being the peoples mouth to God, and God's mouth to the people, that not one word paſſe from his mouth, which makes not for the good of his people, and for the clearing of his account at the great Day. He remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bers well before Whome he is, and to Whome he ſpeakes <hi>in pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er,</hi> and from Whome he ſpeakes <hi>in preaching.</hi> And he conſiders, as he can the infinite diſtance betwixt Majeſtie and Nothing; and now how fixedly doth he looke to Him who is the <hi>Middle perſon,</hi> and having <hi>laid His hand upon Both,</hi> ſtands as a ſcreen, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>twixt <hi>everlaſting Burning,</hi> and this <hi>peice of dried ſtubble,</hi> as in it ſelfe conſidered: and ſo rolling himſelfe upon This <hi>one Mediatour,</hi> and caſting himſelfe into the hands of His Spirit; and truſting in His ſupply, he falls to his worke, and now what advantage hath hee, or have his hearers by addition of this prayer? that is the Queſtion, and the anſwer thereunto, you muſt make unto your God; onely this which we have heard, we will ſay more, which you know is a Miniſters <hi>Motto,</hi> or ſhould be, <q>
                        <hi>Nuſquam doceo, ubi non moveo: Nuſquam moveo ubi non doceo,</hi> I never teach ſavingly, where I doe not move or ſtirre feelingly; that is prae<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vailingly: nor doe I ever ſo move, where I doe not ſo teach,</q> ſo we leave this upon your thoughts, and proceed to one Reaſon more.</p>
                  <p>Fifthly, To our ſeeming, it is a very ſinfull doeing to adde this prayer to the end of our owne, and this upon a threefold ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, You glad the hearts of them that ſhould not be gladded, the wicked we meane; if yon have not heard it ſaid by them, we have once and againe, <hi>What a Brave Miniſter have we to day?</hi> Why? <hi>he ſaid the Lords prayer twice to day</hi> (and oh how ſweetly did he ſay it!) and that was all they obſerved; for the addition of that prayer, rendred him ſo gracious in their eyes, and his Ser<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon ſo ſweet. Certainly we muſt not <hi>glad the hearts of wicked ones,</hi> for then we glad <hi>That Wicked-One.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Secondly, Ye muſt not make the wicked Blaſpheme in Calling God, <hi>Father;</hi> and <hi>Chriſt accurſed;</hi> but this they will doe in ſpight of your heart; for they and they onely will ſay it after you,
<pb n="58" facs="tcp:117967:31"/> and if they ſhould be aſleep, as Commonly they are, all the time of your praying, yet they will awaken at this prayer, or if, while you are running it over with the <hi>ſpeed of a good Clark,</hi> they ſhould chance to nod at the firſt or ſecond Petition, yet they will be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fectly awaked at that <hi>ſignall Concluſion, AMEN</hi>—But wee forbeare—for <hi>Nemo libentèr moratur in aſperis.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Thirdly, Yee <hi>ſad</hi> them, whome the Lord would not have <hi>ſad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ded,</hi> yee ſad the hearts, we thinke, of all the truly Godly there; They cannot endure to heare the Name of God prophaned, That ſweeteſt Name, <hi>Father,</hi> Blaſphemed; their <hi>onely Lord,</hi> cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led <hi>accurſed;</hi> They cannot endure it, it is more greivous to them to heare this within the meeting place, than ſee their filthy Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verſation without We tell you againe; The Truely Godly can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not endure to heare this, they can with much more patience heare their Earthly father abuſed, &amp;c. But their heavenly Father, <hi>Who loved them,</hi> and <hi>Gave His Son unto them;</hi> and them unto His Son: and this Son of God, Who, taking their nature, hath redeemed their Soules from all adverſitie, waſhing them in His owne blood; we were ſaying, they cannot endure to heare their <hi>Father Blaſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>phemed.</hi> nor their Lord <hi>called accurſed;</hi> nor that Signall Word, <hi>Amen</hi>—ecchoed forth by perſons little better than <hi>Quakers</hi> and <hi>Ranters;</hi> damnable <hi>Hereticks; wicked and ſinners before the Lord exceedingly.</hi> But wee have done: Theſe are our Reaſons, why a Godly Miniſter may not adde the Lord s prayer to th' end of his owne. Onely you will remember here what an Excellent Man ſaid; <q>
                        <hi>It is Better to occaſion wrath in the Bad, than greife in the Good.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
               </div>
            </div>
            <div n="8" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. VIII. And fift <hi>Querie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>Q.</hi> V. <q>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">W</seg>Hether <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray by giving them formes of prayer to ſay? And, (which may be queried there<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>upon) Whether a Parent can teach his child to pray, by ſetting <hi>formes</hi> of prayer before him whereafter to pray?</q> As thus (for wee would be cleare, as to the holding-forth our meaning, and perſwaſion, in
<pb n="59" facs="tcp:117967:31"/> this matter) <q>here, Child, is a forme of prayer, when you pray ſay as you ſee here is preſcribed unto you.</q>
               </p>
               <p>That this ought to be, we meane, That a child may and ought be taught to pray by formes of prayer ſet before him, is affirmed and argued from <hi>Johns</hi> practiſe with his Diſciples. Now our per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaſion is, That <hi>John</hi> did not give his Diſciples, nor ſhould a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent give his child any <hi>forme of prayer</hi> whereafter to pray. And if he ſhall ſo doe, we are inclined to thinke, he hath not by ſo do<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, taught his child to pray, we meane, by giving the child a forme whereafter to pray.</p>
               <p>We will heare, as hitherto we have don, what we have heard ſaid, for the holding forth the Affirmative; and</p>
               <p>Firſt, This is forced againſt us, without any ſhew of reaſon, as we conceive, <q>That we allow not a parent to teach his child to pray.</q>
               </p>
               <p>Truely we would not ſay it for a world, for we know it is a pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rents Duty to teach his Child to pray, and to make it their very worke and their buiſineſſe, that their Child may be ſtill Learning at that high worke.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <q>
                     <hi>But this cannot be done, but by giving them a forme of words wherebyto pray.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We think, yes; it may, by Gods bleſſing upon the Parents faithfull and Conſtant endeavour, this way; and that a forme of prayer preſcribed will rather hinder than further the worke, as was ſaid before.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <q>
                     <hi>But ye, in ſo ſaying, doe Croſſe,</hi> I verily beleive, <hi>the practiſe of moſt the Godly all over the world.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is but your Faith, and it is quickly ſaid, and impoſſible to be Proved, <q>
                     <hi>That moſt of the Godly give their Children formes of prayer, to teach them to pray;</hi>
                  </q> though you doe ſo, you will not conclude that others ſo doe. You may be, as was ſaid, <hi>norma pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lica,</hi> as a patterne or ſtandard to your owne people and Chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, not ſo to others.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, <q>
                     <hi>We are ſure we have a ſure patterne for it, John Baptiſt himſelfe.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We had rather, you had ſaid, we have a ſure word for it from the Lord God Himſelfe: Yet we refuſe not this patterne; As farre from Deſpiſing what <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> did, as we are from reject<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing
<pb n="60" facs="tcp:117967:32"/> what <hi>John the Baptiſt</hi> ſaid; And this you ſay <hi>John</hi> did, <hi>he</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Luke 11. 1.</note> 
                  <hi>taught his Diſciples to pray;</hi> we yeild it; and that every Godly parent is to make him his patterne, in teaching his Child to pray.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, <q>
                     <hi>The<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                           <desc>•</desc>
                        </gap> he muſt give his Child a forme of prayer, not poſſible elſe to teach him to pray. Beſides ſo taught John his Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ciples to pray, as worthy</hi> Hild: <hi>ſayes, by giving them formes of prayer to ſay.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>We move heavily here, becauſe againſt the Streame, even of the Learned in this very matter; <hi>John's teaching his Diſciples to pray.</hi> Yet if we have the Mind of Gods Spirit, and the tide of the Scriptures with us, we ſhall hold-on our courſe, and attaine our end anon. To this wee ſay then; <q>That it is very poſſible to teach a child to pray, without giving them formes of prayer to ſay;</q> And ſo wee are perſwaded <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray; wee would be rightly underſtood here, ſpeaking after the manner of men, and according to the poſſibilitie, our heavenly Father, for his onely Sonnes ſake, hath made poſſible unto men. It is not cleare to us, nor doe wee thinke it poſſible for any man to make it cleare to himſelfe from the word of God, <hi>That John taught his Diſciples to pray by giving them formes of prayer to ſay;</hi> He taught them to pray, that is out of all queſtion, for ſo wee read, and ſo he did his dutie, and full-up to his charge. But that <hi>he gave them formes of prayer to ſay,</hi> this is of mans adding, and upon an ungrounded ſuppoſition, as wee conceive; <q>
                     <hi>That it was not poſſible for John, but by thoſe formes to teach his Diſciples to pray.</hi>
                  </q> Wee conceive, yes; And that <hi>John</hi> in thoſe dayes, and that a godly parent in theſe our dayes, can skill better to teach his child to pray without formes of prayer, than with them.</p>
               <p>Surely <hi>John</hi> did teach his Diſciples, <hi>To Whome they</hi> were to ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dreſſe themſelves in prayer, after he had told them firſt what a ſolemne and ſacred worke it was; And then acquainted them with the <hi>New and living way unto the Father, through Whome and</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 14. 6. Heb. 7. 19. 10. 19, 20. Eph. 2. 18.</note> 
                  <hi>by Whoſe hand, introduction, or hand-leading they have acceſſe unto the Father.</hi> He manifeſted unto them, as he could, for that was his great worke to doe, The <hi>Meſſias;</hi> he ſhewed Him openly be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore them; and what loſt ones they were without Him. And what glorious creatures they are, being <hi>found in Him, not having
<pb n="61" facs="tcp:117967:32"/> their owne righteouſneſſe,</hi> which more <hi>inſnareth the ſoule, and in<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dangereth it alſo, than the groſſeſt ſins doe.</hi> It is a grave and weigh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tie<note place="margin">D<hi rend="sup">r</hi> 
                     <hi>G</hi> trial. <hi>gr. 1. 53.</hi>
                  </note> ſpeech which that excellent man hath; <q>
                     <hi>There is no danger to be lifted-up hy the righteouſneſſe of another, for it is without us, wee can't vainly boaſt of it, for that faith, that apprehends it, emptyes us firſt of our ſelves, and goeth out to another for it. But ſanctification being a worke wrought in us, wee are apt to doate on that, as too much upon any excellency in our ſelves.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>Surely <hi>John</hi> beate them off from their <hi>owne righteouſneſſe,</hi> the putting <hi>any confidence in their fleſh;</hi> he clubbed downe that <hi>Mon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſter,</hi> for ſo <hi>Luther</hi> calls it; he treated much with them, as wee reade, <hi>about Repentance towards God, and faith in the Lord Jeſus<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Chriſt;</hi> and dealt with them much, ſpecially with his Diſciples, in this, what <hi>blind, poore, naked, emptie ones they muſt be in their owne ſenſe and feeling,</hi> before it can ever enter into their thoughts to pray <hi>for the anoynting with eye-ſalve,</hi> that <hi>they may ſee a far-off,</hi> or before they will looke after faith, which pitcheth the ſoule up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on Chriſt, and then fetcheth in all that maketh truly rich, and put<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teth upon the ſoule the glorious cloathing of the Saints, emptieth the ſoule, and then fills it with the <hi>fulneſſe of God, through Jeſus Chriſt.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Thus wee conceive, and by no other meanes did <hi>John</hi> teach his Diſciples to pray; Wee cannot reach to his words, and may ſeeme too bold in making offer that way; But thus wee conceive, and wee ſay it againe, <hi>John</hi> taught his Diſciples to pray. And not by preſcribing them certain formes of prayer to ſay, when they come before their God. And this wee conceive to be the ready way a godly parent takes now to teach his childe to pray to his God. What way muſt he take? This he may know better than wee. But he muſt teach the childe to know God firſt; or, if to pray firſt, then to pray, that he may know Him, beleeve in Him and obey Him; And this the parent cannot well teach the childe till he hath taught the poore ſimple creature to know it ſelfe firſt in ſome meaſure, and what need he hath <hi>of a God in Chriſt</hi> (for ſo the parent dropps into the childe, as he can, a little veſſell, and a leſſe mouth to receive in, and how much falls by, and how little is in when it is there in ſuch matters as theſe are?) But this (wee were ſaying) the godly parent endeavours to doe now a little
<pb n="62" facs="tcp:117967:33"/> and then a little, A little more knowledge of himſelfe, what he is in the <hi>firſt Adam,</hi> as he was borne in the world, <hi>a childe of death,</hi> of, or <hi>under wrath there;</hi> what they are, that are tranſlated or ta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken out of the <hi>firſt Adam, in whome all dye,</hi> and are <hi>pl<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>nted in the ſecond Adam, in whome all are made alive:</hi> This and what more wee cannot ſo well tell the godly parent treateth w<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>th his childe about, and ſo <hi>teacheth him to pray;</hi> and a farre more ready way doth he take by ſo doing, then if he could give unto his hands All the prayer-books that are in the world. This is our perſwaſion, and that wee are ſo taught out of the word of God. And truly wee are the more inclined hereunto.</p>
               <p>Firſt, By reaſon that this was the manner of all the godly in the holy Scriptures, teaching their<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> children to pray ſo farre as wee can learne thereby, and have any diſcerning thereof, held forth before us. Heare his words to <hi>Solomon</hi> his ſonne, they con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>teine much; <hi>Know thou the God of thy father</hi> [A mightie motive<note place="margin">
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> Chro<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 28. 9.</note> to <hi>Solomon</hi> to learne to know the Lord; he had a godly father that knew him, as the father had a godly mother that knew her God; and ſurely taught <hi>David</hi> to know him alſo, <q>
                     <hi>The ſon of</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 8. 6. 16. 116. 16.</note> 
                     <hi>thy handmaid] And ſerve him.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>[<hi>Solomon</hi> muſt know the God of his father, before he can ſerve Him, as his father did. Wee cannot worſhip or pray unto Him, whom wee know not, for in ſo doeing, wee <hi>worſhip wee know not</hi>
                  <note place="margin">John 4. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>2.</note> 
                  <hi>what.] A God.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>A God in Chriſt muſt in ſome meaſure and degree be reveiled to us, before wee can come to God, and plead our matters with Him, in His Sons bleſſed Name, and for His glorious<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ſake; Wee can no more ſerve a God<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> Whom wee know not, then wee can be ſaved by a Chriſt whom wee never heard of: for that were, as if a captive held under the power of <hi>death, ſin, devill,</hi> and <hi>hell,</hi> ſhould be redeemed by a price paid by one, whom never before nor after he had an<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> knowledge of; or as if God for Chriſts ſake <hi>ſhould ſave us, and yet never by any meanes or in any meaſure make That Chriſt knowne to us.</hi> He muſt by ſome meanes or <hi>other be reveiled to them, who, being growne up to the uſe of reaſon, were ever ſaved by him.</hi> Theſe are excellent Dr <hi>Tuckneyes</hi> words. We ſhould, as a<note place="margin">Sermon upon <hi>Acts 4. 12.</hi>
                  </note> godly parent will with his child, and whom he will teach to pray, goe through the forementioned Scriptures which containes ſo
<pb n="63" facs="tcp:117967:33"/> much, but wee have attained our ſcope thereby, A godly paren<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap> teacheth his child to know God firſt what He is in himſelfe out of Chriſt <hi>meere wrath,</hi> a <hi>conſumeing fire;</hi> and as ſuch an one he cannot be ſerved. Then to know Him a God in Chriſt, and a Fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, and ſo He is ſerved, and well-pleaſed with the ſervice if it be in truth.</p>
               <p>Wee paſſe on and ſhall paſſe over <hi>David's</hi> Catechiſme and <hi>Bathſheba's</hi> alſo, whereof wee reade in the booke of the <hi>Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>verbs,</hi> but not a word there of teaching the childe to pray by <hi>form<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>s of prayer.</hi> Wee thinke that <hi>Paul's</hi> direction to parents how they ſhould order their children, and ſpecial<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>y how to teach them to pray<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> contains as much to that m<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>tter as doth that Cate<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>chiſme, <q>
                     <hi>Bring them up,</hi> ſo wee read it;</q> the word is, <hi>nurſe them</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Eph. 6. 4. 1 Theſ. 2. 7.</note> 
                  <hi>up.</hi> As a nurſe, ſaith he, in another place, takes care of the bodies concernments, ſo doe ye parents of your childrens ſoules concern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ments. <hi>Nurſe them up in the nurture;</hi> It implyes all care and dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence about the inward man ſtill, that all be done as matters ſhall require, whether they <hi>exhort, charge, reproove, correct,</hi> or <hi>inſtruct, that all be done to the childe in a motherly way,</hi> or, as <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith, <hi>as a father his children;</hi> remembring ſtill, that godlineſſe is a rich and ſure trade, if the childe be taught well to follow it.] <hi>And admonition</hi> [A dealing about the mind of the childe ſtill, rectify<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing or moulding of it betime, as the nurſe doth the mould of the head, when its tender: It ſignifies a dropping or putting into the<note place="margin">Eph. <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>. 4<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                  </note> mind ſtill. It is a thruſting of ſomewhat upon the childe ſtill with an holy violence, which may mind him of his Lord Jehovah his God; ſo that the child may ſee, that, what his parents ſpeakes to him comes from his Lord, and tendeth to this, to bring the mind of the child up to the Lord, there to fix and pitch his ſoule for ever] <hi>Zanch:</hi> (ſo wee are told) ſpeakes uſefully to this as his manner is, upon this verſe, where he tells us the manner of all the godly in the primitive times, and what courſe <hi>Abraham</hi> tooke to teach his children. Wee verily thinke wee may adde, <q>
                     <hi>to pray.</hi>
                  </q> And what way alſo <hi>L<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>is</hi> the <hi>grandmother</hi> and <hi>Eunice the mother</hi>
                  <note place="margin">2 Tim. 1. 5.</note> taught their young <hi>Timothy,</hi> wee will adde againe, <hi>to pray.</hi> The very way which the old Chriſtians (<hi>priſci chriſtiani</hi>) did take to<note place="margin">3. 1.</note> teach their children [<hi>to pray] by bringing them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord.</hi> And all this is but according to the
<pb n="64" facs="tcp:117967:34"/> preſcript and charge unto us from the Lord God Allmightie; <hi>Theſe words which I command thee this day ſhall be in thine heart,</hi>
                  <note place="margin">Deut. 6. 6, 7.</note> 
                  <hi>and thou ſhalt teach them diligently (thy children) and ſhalt talke of them, when thou ſitteſt in thine houſe, and when thou walkeſt by the way, and when thou lyeſt downe, and when thou riſeſt up.</hi> And this is the way, wee are perſwaded in our hearts, every godly pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rent muſt take, who makes it his buiſineſſe to teach his childe to pray, for this was the manner of the godly in dayes of old: which is our firſt reaſon.</p>
               <p>Secondly, And in the ſecond place we are apt to thinke, That to bring up a childe in the nurture and admonition of the Lord, is the onely ready way to teach a childe to pray; and not to give him formes of prayer to ſay; becauſe theſe formes hinder rather than further the worke, carrying the childe on in ſuch a high worke (the calling upon God in prayer) by the Eye upon the formes, or by the memorie, which is all one, whereas he ſhould underſtand what he doth, and know Him in ſome meaſure and degree, Whom he calleth upon.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, If to give a childe a forme of prayer, when you pray <hi>ſay theſe words,</hi> were to teach him to pray, then to teach a childe to pray is the eaſieſt worke in the world, &amp; of as quicke diſpatch, for ſo eaſie it is, and as quickly done, to give a childe a forme, whereby to pray. But no godly parent ever found it from ancient dayes to this day an eaſie worke and of quick diſpatch to teach his childe to pray, no more than it is an eaſie worke or the worke of a day <hi>to rule well his owne houſe, and to have his children in ſub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>jection</hi>
                  <note place="margin">1 Tim. 3. 4.</note> 
                  <hi>with all gravitie,</hi> which falls-in fully with theſe words be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore-cited, to <hi>bring them up in the nurture and admonition of the Lord,</hi> whereby to teach his childe to pray. It is not the worke of a day, or two, as was ſaid in another caſe, but the worke of every day, while the childe is under the parents eye and eare, <hi>To teach the childe to pray:</hi> Nay to adde this; It is eaſie for the vileſt per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in your Nationall Church to teach a childe to pray, if to give him a forme to pray be to teach him to pray; for ſo much he or ſhe can doe having learnt ſo much themſelves to pray that way. But ſure he or ſhe muſt be taught to pray and helpe by the good Spirit to pray, before they can teach their childe to pray.</p>
               <p>Fourthly, And in the fourth place, we thinke, it at leaſt coaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth
<pb n="65" facs="tcp:117967:34"/> neere the brinke of preſumption, nay is it not downe-right preſumption to teach a childe to pray by giving him a forme of prayer to ſay? As thus, for, as wee ſaid, ſo plaine wee would be; <q>Deare childe, what ever thy ignorance is of God the Father, thou prayeſt unto; or of God the Sonne <hi>manifeſt in the fleſh,</hi> in whoſe name thou prayeſt; what ever mercy thou haſt received, and wouldſt praiſe God for; what ever want thou feeleſt, and wouldſt pray to Him for a ſupply from Him; what ever thy ſinnes are thou ſhouldſt confeſſe before Him, yet doe thou, childe, pray in theſe words, according to this very forme I have preſcribed unto thee.</q> Surely wee will not feare to ſay, this were preſumption; and, ſo, as may be feared, it will be accounted be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fore his God.</p>
               <p>Fifthly, Beſides, and ſo wee have done, In ſo doeing, wee meane ſo teaching this childe to pray by a forme, The parent hath told a loud lye in the eares of God, and of all the godly, for he tells God and men both, <hi>he hath taught his childe to pray,</hi> when indeed there is no ſuch thing done; he hath not taught his childe to pray; for by his owne confeſſion he hath given his childe a <hi>forme</hi> whereby to pray, which forme will become a prayer well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pleaſing unto God, when copper becomes gold, the bramble a vine the Moone a Sunne, or when the <hi>Sunne</hi> painted on a ſigne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſt ſhall ſhine in the firmament of Heaven. And ſo wee have taken in your reaſons, and examined the reaſonableneſſe of them, That a parent teaching his childe to pray, muſt give him a forme whereafter to pray. Wee have given in our reaſons alſo from ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cred Scripture, as wee ſuppoſe, That by giving your childe a forme whereby to pray, is not to teach the childe to pray. But let it be committed to Him, Who <hi>guides into all truth.</hi>
               </p>
            </div>
            <div n="9" type="chapter">
               <head>CHAP. IX. Sixt and laſt <hi>Querie.</hi>
               </head>
               <p>
                  <hi>
                     <seg rend="decorInit">Q</seg>.</hi> VI. WEE are come to our ſixt and laſt <hi>Querie,</hi> to give<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> in our thoughts thereunto; <q>Whether a Godly parent hath any Command from Chriſt, to teach their children the Lords prayer, thereafter to pray, ſaying the very ſame words?</q>
               </p>
               <pb n="66" facs="tcp:117967:35"/>
               <p>Wee ſaid, <hi>a Command from Chriſt,</hi> for wee ſuppoſe it granted, That a Godly perſon will, in every thing he doth, ſpecially in matters of ſo high concernment, look firſt to his Warrant; <hi>This I doe, I have a ſure Word for what I doe.</hi> And having his Lords<note place="margin">S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>quis De<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                        <desc>••</desc>
                     </gap>h <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>empe<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>et jam ut da<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>ne u<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> a <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>en tum Mand<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="3 letters">
                        <desc>•••</desc>
                     </gap> tis eſt h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>h<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>r? D<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>um <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>uth<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap> e<g ref="char:cmbAbbrStroke">̄</g>. Lum 3. 38.</note> word for that he doth <hi>ſhould he be condemned by an hundred worlds</hi> (to uſe excellent <hi>Calvins</hi> words) he has enough to beare him out<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> 
                  <hi>his Lord Commanded him.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>But, Sir; before we proceed we crave leave to give-in a ſho<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>t account, wherefore wee meddle with this here; your ſelfe giving the occaſion thereof, and little leſſe, though perhaps againſt your purpoſe, provoking us ſo to doe: Our account in ſhort is this: Our Miniſter in the courſe of Catechizing his people (as was hinted before in our Introductive part) fell upon the Expoſition of the <hi>Lord's Prayer,</hi> and as an Introduction thereunto, he put ſome <hi>Queries</hi> about this prayer, and among others, of ſpeciall uſe all<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> as we thought, this was one; <q>
                     <hi>Whether a Godly parent ought to teach his Children this prayer?</hi>
                  </q> and ſo reſolved it from Scrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture, as wee ſuppoſe, in the Negative <hi>he ought not.</hi> But how were the Godly people (they ſeemed ſuch to be and we would hope they, ſome of them, more than ſeeme) ſtirred at this? as much every whit as the ungodly are, when their Idol is pulled at, to pull it-away; for whereas (we tell you the words of one of them) they could have pulled out their eyes for their Miniſter, before he meddled with the Lord's prayer, now they were more enclined, at leaſt, to pull out their Miniſters eyes from him, than their owne for him. Truely we judge Charitablie, as our dutie is, and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceive good hope, that the Oppoſers or contrary-minded herein, ſome of them, are godly in the maine, (onely ſeduced or miſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guided by former guides) though one of them well ſtricken in yeares, was taught that prayer at the firſt, when he was a Childe, and ſeldome ſaid any other to that day, as hath been told to us by one that did know, if any did To Conclude our narrative part; Theſe perſons thus moved and diſquieted, addreſſed themſelves to you Sir, as their <hi>Oracle,</hi> whereas their Dutie was to have Conſul<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ted with the Scriptures, our Miniſter laid before them, and after<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wards, as occaſion required, with himſelfe; But it is not our <hi>man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ner</hi> to doe things after their <hi>right manner.</hi>
               </p>
               <p>Though yet we Blame them not for adviſeing with you, onely
<pb n="67" facs="tcp:117967:35"/> wee ſay they ſhould have ſearched the Scriptures, and have advi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſed with their Miniſter firſt. Your Anſwer to them was ſweet and comely, farre otherwiſe than was reported by one of them, who may be as much taken with <hi>that prayer,</hi> as ſome are with that they make an Idol. Onely this you ſaid to them, which they lookt for and it pleaſed them well, and it was aboundantly enough to marre all our Miniſter had ſaid from the Lord unto them, <q>
                     <hi>That you teach your Children that prayer, or allow it they ſhould be ſo taught.</hi>
                  </q> And now wee are forced to call your practiſe into Que<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtion, which truly, but for the Truth's ſake, wee ſhall doe unwil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lingly, and ſo wee ſhall ſtate the Queſtion in the Negative; <q>
                     <hi>That a Godly Parent ought not to teach his Children the Lords prayer.</hi>
                  </q> You hold the Affirmative, for thereafter you practiſe, wee would hope you can make full proof that your practiſe is Godly. So, Sir, we crave your reaſons, at leaſt, wee crave your leave to gueſſe at them, by what we have heard from others, and ſo to ſett downe, as may be allowed us in theſe caſes, what proba<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly your reaſons may be to hold-forth your practice with your children to be godly and holy, full-up to your rule and preſcrip<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion in Gods word, whereafter you order, wee hope, your whole converſation, your ſayings and doeings before your people, and your whole houſe, your children ſpecially the maine and principall parts, and your cheife goods there: for by your well-ruling of them, and care over them, you will make full proofe what care you take of the Churches of God; for he who knowes how to rule his own houſe well, is in a good poſture of ſpirit to rule well the houſe of God—But this was ſpoken before in the ſecond Treatiſe, relating to the Lords Supper <hi>pag.</hi> 19. This wee were ſaying your ruling well your own houſe, will be a good Teſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>moriall, that you rule well as a good Steward in the Houſe of the living God. Therefore we hope, you can give good reaſon for all you doe in your owne houſe, which you order, we would hope, in deſire and endeavour, as thoſe <hi>whoſe praiſe is in the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpell.</hi> Probably your reaſons are theſe, or ſuch like, to theſe; for wee will not mention here any of that, which went before, one wee would remind you of the ſame.</p>
               <p>Firſt, <q>
                     <hi>Can there be a more excellent prayer, and more compre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>henſive than the Lords prayer is?</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <pb n="68" facs="tcp:117967:36"/>
               <p>Verily, No; And therefore is it ſo takeing in the world; for if any forme may be uſed whereafter to pray, uſeing the <hi>very ſame words,</hi> then this forme above any. No prayer being more excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent, nor more comprehenſive. But therefore thinke wee, the more unfit to be taught a Child, the more unſuitable to his underſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing. The prayer is excellent, conſidered in it ſelfe, and as you may be able to conſider of it; but it hath no excellencie with a childe; he ſpeakes as a child, he underſtands as a child, he thinkes, or rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoneth as a childe; And with due regard to all this, you muſt ſpeake to him, and reaſon with him, in lower matters than are the contents of this prayer.</p>
               <p>Secondly, <q>
                     <hi>You may ſay, I muſt reaſon with him about God, and Chriſt, and what manner of perſon He is, and how He is to be ſerved; but theſe are no low matters, but high, and much above the reach of a childs underſtanding.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>It is readily graunted. Yet you may conſider, it is one thing to drop-in, as into a verie narrow mouthed veſſell, drop by drop, and to powre in all at once; wee meane, To deale with a childe word after word, then to ſee how the firſt word taketh, before you deale with him about the ſecond; And to give him ſix lines together, whereas each line ſingle and apart, comprehends more of God and of Chriſt in it, of grace and glory by Him, then doe the viſible Heavens; O the vaſt comprehenſion of this Prayer! And the ſhallowneſſe of a childs; ſhall wee ſay of a mans com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>prehenſion about it! You may teach your child to ſay it, ſo you may your <hi>Parrot</hi> too; and teaching him it altogether to ſay it, as you, in your pulpit, he will underſtand it as much as the Parrot doth; and by ſo ſaying it, you ſhall teach the people to under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand it, if not all, yet but little better alſo; You may put this prayer, as to the words of it, into the mouth of your childe, but he comprehends it no more, than doth the darkneſſe the light.</p>
               <p>Thirdly, <q>You may ſay as wee heare others doe, <hi>It is a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mendable thing, and well becomeing a godly parent ſure, to teach his child to call God father, though</hi> as <hi>Hieron</hi> ſaith, <hi>he doth but liſpe out father.</hi>
                  </q>
               </p>
               <p>You know, and you know it for your good, To call God fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther, or rather to cry, <hi>Abba Father,</hi> is as was ſaid, of the Spirits teaching, I cannot liſpe <hi>Abba Father,</hi> but as He hath <hi>adopted</hi> mee,
<pb n="69" facs="tcp:117967:36"/> that is, in Jeſus Chriſt, in Whome alone He is become the Father of mercies unto mee, ſaith that learned man Dr <hi>K:</hi> Chap: 4. <hi>
                     <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>:</hi> 115. Yet it is graunted, you are to teach your childe to call <hi>God father,</hi> as you can. And you have heard of the method or ready way you may take till you know a better in teaching your child, that great and high leſſon. But everie thing is comely in its due time and order. Wee conceive you are to teach your child firſt, to call himſelfe <hi>rebell againſt this heavenly Father;</hi> that he was borne into the world with his backe againſt him, (being borne a child of wrath aſſoone as he was a child of a man:) an enemie to this Father, even <hi>enmitie</hi> it ſelfe, and an <hi>hater</hi> of Him. And then wee take it, the child is to be farther queſtioned (and that is the beſt way of teaching by queſtioning) whether this <hi>en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mitie</hi> is in any meaſure or degree diſcovered to him, by the Spirit with the Word, and <hi>ſhine in him?</hi> (for enmitie cannot become friendſhip, though enemies may be made friends) <hi>enmitie muſt be ſlaine.</hi> This wee conceive the child muſt be taught firſt, before he can be taught to call God Father, after a due manner and a right underſtanding.</p>
               <div n="4" type="section">
                  <head>SECT. IV.</head>
                  <p>NOw wee take leave to give-in our reaſons, as few and as breifely as wee have taken-in yours; <q>
                        <hi>Wherefore it is not becomeing a godly parent to teach his child the Lords prayer.</hi>
                     </q> Wee ſhall not recall here neither, but reminde you onely of what went before, that caried verie levell to this verie ſcope.</p>
                  <p>Firſt, It is cleane croſſe to the right method of teaching to ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>erciſe the childes memory firſt, for it is to teach your child as you would teach your Parrot, between whom you know to put a wide difference, Sith God hath made them ſo to differ, <hi>Who tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Job 35. 11.</note> 
                     <hi>us more then the beaſts of the earth, and makes us wiſer then the fowles of heaven.</hi> You teach a child as becometh a childe to be taught; You teach a fowle, bird or beaſt, as is comely for them to be taught; beſides, you put a greater difference betwixt earth<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly and heavenly matters; ſenſuall and ſpirituall; and accordingly you muſt vary in your teaching. This may ſuffice for the firſt.</p>
                  <p>Secondly, You would have your deare childe to be a gainer
<pb n="68" facs="tcp:117967:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="69" facs="tcp:117967:37"/>
                     <gap reason="duplicate" extent="1 page">
                        <desc>〈1 page duplicate〉</desc>
                     </gap>
                     <pb n="70" facs="tcp:117967:38"/> by your teaching. Wee beſeech you aske him, now you have taught him the Lords prayer, what he hath gained by your tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ching? Our perſwaſion is you will find his gaine to be but ſmall; onely whereas when time was he ſaid it as a child, <hi>Parrot</hi>-like now, being growne-up, he ſayes it with <hi>more grace</hi> in the eare of the hearer, ſaying it like a <hi>Clarke,</hi> but perhaps with as little grace in the heart as he ſaid in before when he was a child. But yet we cannot graunt you, That by all your teaching, you have taught your child the <hi>Lords prayer<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
                     </hi> for if you have taught him to read it, he can teach himſelfe to ſay it without your helpe.</p>
                  <p>Thirdly, You ſhould not doe as all the wicked of the world doe; we meane, of your Nationall Church, who have onely this to ſhew for their Chriſtianitie, and whereby to make full proofe thereof, <hi>That they were borne in your Church, and waſhed there:</hi> Wee thinke it is not comely for you to doe as they doe; they hold to that Injunction appointed them by their <hi>Prieſt,</hi> as he by the Biſhop, whereof hereafter. All the wicked perſons in your Church, we are perſwaded, not one excepted, no not the verieſt varlet there, but they all teach it their children, they ſhall have it, as they themſelves had it, <hi>by tradition from their parents.</hi> Theſe were taught their <hi>Pater noſter;</hi> (they underſtand the Latine as well as the Engliſh, and the Greeke too) <hi>their Creed,</hi> and the <hi>ten Commandements;</hi> and ſo much they will teach their children, either by themſelves or another, and having learnt ſo much with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out the booke, they have learnt enough for themſelves and their children after them. You that know the Country-folke and their uſage, know it ſo to be, having heard them ſaying ſo much you know not how often. You know better, and you muſt doe better. You would not be numbred among the wicked in after time, you muſt not doe, as they doe now. And yet to excuſe them a little, and blame you more. Theſe, as they conceived, had a command or charge laid upon them, when time was, by their guides and rulers of their Church then; their charge is expreſſe in theſe words; <q>
                        <hi>At the laſt end the Prieſt calling the God-fathers and God<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mothers together, ſhall ſay th<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="2 letters">
                              <desc>••</desc>
                           </gap> exhortation following, the fulleſt part whereof is this, Yee ſhall provide that theſe children ſhall learne the Creed, the Lords prayer, and the ten Commandements in the Engliſh tongue.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <pb n="71" facs="tcp:117967:38"/>
                  <p>You will not<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> ground your practiſe hereupon, for ſo you would practiſe after that heathen Prieſt, whom you may know; This Prieſt juſtifies his cuſtomes as to Church-matters, by quoteing (as we have heard) the <hi>Service-Booke,</hi> and thoſe cuſtomes in uſe then, which he followes to a tittle; for as to that ſacred Booke, wee cannot tell whether he ſo much as lookes upon it; certaine it is he hateth the contents there with his heart; for he hateth to heare it, and to be informed by it. You abhorre wee hope, ſuch doeings, which were in uſe amongſt us, when <hi>Tyrannie and Pope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rie</hi> were in their Tropick, or Zenith, the higheſt verticall point; then indeed theſe words were in uſe, which ſome will call a com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mand or charge. But ſo will not you, for you (wee would hope) doe bleſſe God day and<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> night, who hath delivered His Church (wee meane, not that you call <hi>Nationall,</hi> for that is in <hi>Egypt</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Acts 7. 39.</note> ſtill, being never out, or if a dayes journey out, yet returning thereunto, and is there <hi>in heart,</hi> there it would be as before in the Biſhops dayes) wee ſay <hi>His Church</hi> from out of that more than <hi>Egyptian darkneſſe,</hi> whereunto it ſhall returne no more; being the <hi>Vineyard of red wine,</hi> which <hi>He</hi> hath undertaken <hi>to water eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry moment, and that nothing hurt it, to keepe it night and day.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Fourthly, And in the laſt place; you ſhould not teach your child that, which you muſt unteach againe: what is taught and learnt by the precepts of men, muſt be untaught and unlearnt by the precept of God. But, wee thinke, wee have prooved, That the teaching by formes, is but the teaching of men, and they have their warrant, onely by precept from men: You know what is ſtoried of a godly Matron, after her heart was turned, and ſett upon Chriſt, It was told us once, and wee heard it twice; before <hi>ſhe was humbled,</hi> as was ſaid of <hi>Manaſſeh,</hi> ſhe had taught her chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren<note place="margin">2 Chr. 33. 19.</note> as you doe, <hi>the Lords prayer,</hi> and ſo ſhe confeſſed, but come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing <hi>to her ſelfe,</hi> or to uſe her owne words, to her <hi>right minde;</hi> ſhe endeavoured all ſhe could to unteach them againe; what ſhe ef<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fected with all her indeavour is more then wee can tell. But you may tell us when you goe about it, what an hard and difficult worke you ſhall find it to be to unlearne your children what you have ſo eaſily and quickly taught them, (if it had been good, it had not been ſo eaſily taught, nor ſo quickly learnt) In the meane time, wee can tell our ſelves, That children and grown-folke alſo
<pb n="72" facs="tcp:117967:39"/> are as hardly beat off from their formes, as an hungry Maſtyffe is from his prey. Naturally wee cleave as faſt to formes of all fa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſhions, and theſe to us, as the fleſh cleaveth to the bone, and ſinne to the fleſh. How hard a thing is it then to leave a <hi>forme,</hi> and looke to the <hi>power?</hi> when in leaving this wee muſt overcome a <hi>double Nature,</hi> our owne firſt, and that, which cuſtome hath made our owne, or ſecond Nature, having learnt it from our Cradle, and growne up in the practiſe of it.</p>
                  <p>Take heed good Sir, Looke over your ſcholars, and conſider them well, you may teach them in theſe eaſie matters, or pleaſe you, they can learn without teaching, ſuch eaſie leſſons, ſix lines in ſix minutes time; <hi>Lenocinante Natura,</hi> their nature is a very bawd hereunto, to <hi>learne formes,</hi> and cleave unto them, when ſhe hath done; but when you come to unlearne them, which you muſt doe, if ever you learne them right, you ſhall finde it a worke im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſſible to fleſh and blood. Why! What thinke you? A childe or a man prayes, as you have taught him, and exactly well he thinkes, for he ſayes the <hi>Lords prayer</hi> (without either feare or wit, becauſe without underſtanding) Can you thinke now that he will be drawne off from this praying by a forme? why not? be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe (1) his father taught him ſo to pray, and he knew well what he did, for he was a Miniſter of Chriſt: <hi>father</hi> and <hi>mother</hi> are deare names, and what they teach is like to abide with them, ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ally if it put the <hi>fleſh to no coſt;</hi> but however, it is like to ſticke, becauſe a leſſon from a father comes with <hi>authoritie,</hi> and ſo with more advantage to prevaile. (2) Becauſe he can pray by <hi>a forme,</hi> yet reade nothing to purpoſe, nor heare any thing to purpoſe: nor meditate upon any thing to purpoſe that he heares or reades; this is moſt pleaſing to the fleſh. Your child will part as hardly from it as he will part from his <hi>skin,</hi> yea or from his ſinne. Deare Sir, remember what you have read, and adde it, if pleaſe you, to all that, which went before; <hi>He that reades much, and heares much, and meditates much upon what he reades and heares, he prayes much,</hi> (for to meditate and to pray are from the ſame root) perſwade your children to reade much, and heare, and meditate much, that is, to thinke on what they reade and heare (for <hi>thoughts are but exerciſing of the ſoules faculties, you know</hi>) and by the bleſſing of God with you and them, you may teach them to pray, and to ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>count
<pb n="73" facs="tcp:117967:39"/> no more of their formes, one, or more, as to their helpe in that matter, then they doe of anothers <hi>mouth</hi> and <hi>teeth,</hi> thereby to chew their meate; or of anothers feet whereby to goe. <hi>Ye ſhall offer no ſtrange incenſe thereon,</hi> Exod: 30. 9. Mr <hi>Ainſworths</hi> note there-upon is this; <q>
                        <hi>It figured the prayers of the Saints, which muſt be according to the will of God, by His Spirit, and in faith: not after the tradition of men, or will of the fleſh.</hi>
                     </q>
                  </p>
                  <p>Once more and wee have done; Live well before your chil<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dren, wee hope you doe, a readie way alſo to teach them to pray well, for you know the ſaying, <hi>well living is a well teaching;</hi> 
                     <q>and the ſhorteſt way of teaching; a long way about by pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cept, a ſhort way by practiſe or example;</q> 
                     <hi>he that lives well prays well;</hi> and he that beleives much, prayes much, though he ſay not a word. <hi>A good life is a good prayer,</hi> it is <hi>a continued prayer,</hi> as you have read. Wee will cloſe with this; <q>Traine up a child (ſaith the wiſdome of God) <hi>in his way</hi> of Gods preſcribing, and when he is old <hi>he will not depart from it.</hi> As if he had ſaid; <hi>He will be the better for it while he liveth.</hi> Traine up a child in formes<note place="margin">Prov. 22. 6.</note> (according to the wiſdome of the fleſh) and when he is old he will not depart from them;</q> As if wee had ſaid, <hi>he will be the worſe for them while he liveth,</hi> if grace interpoſe not. Theſe are too ſweet to the fleſh, for the fleſh to leave; theſe are all the comfort the fleſh hath while the man is living; but dying ſhall ſtand the man in no more ſtead, than a <hi>paper wall</hi> can defend a<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gainſt a Cannon ſhott, or the <hi>Cawle of the heart</hi> againſt the paw of a Lion. Wee will ſhutt up with this, and ſo call to remem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>brance, That there was an huge great perſon, who had learnt that in his Cradle, which he could not unlearne on his throne; and it was no ſmall diſhonour to him. So may a child be taught a forme of prayer in his cradle, which if, through the favour of the times, he be admitted to the pulpitt, he will uſe there alſo; and ſo exact he will be therein, that all that heare him, may conclude, <hi>he was taught that forme from his cradle.</hi> It is important ſure, and very momentous, elſe <hi>Quintillian</hi> (wee rather mention him) had not been ſo full and large upon it; what choice wee ſhould make of Nurſes, becauſe commonly theſe parle firſt with the child in the morning, and laſt at night, and much all the day long. And if they be bad, not knowing their dutie, or careleſſe of what they know,
<pb n="74" facs="tcp:117967:40"/> wee are like to have, as was once ſaid wirtily, but truely, <hi>a child, or a boy of him all his life long</hi>—The ſumme is this; <hi>Be well ad<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viſed about that you teach your child in the morning of his yeares, he will ſavour of it to the evening of the ſame.</hi> Nurſes or mothers, who ſhould make all, commonly marre all, if ſpeciall grace inter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>poſe not. No more, for this containes much, if not all.</p>
                  <p>Now we will Contract, what hath been ſaid of this ſubject <hi>prayer,</hi> and the ſcope whereto it tends, and give it in this breif.</p>
                  <p>We have ſhewen what a ſerious worke it is; and what a ſlight, and vaine thing <hi>formes</hi> are: wee have declared againſt a wicked mans prayer; for ſo the Lord himſelfe doth: it is an <hi>abomination;</hi> yet it is his dutie to pray; though a greater abomination it is to ſay the <hi>Lords prayer.</hi>
                  </p>
                  <p>Wee have ſhutt it out of the Cloſet; It is too ſhort for Clo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſet-worke. And too long for an <hi>after prayer,</hi> being, who knowes how full of heavenly ſenſe, and ſpirituall meaning. Therefore wee have cutt it off from the Miniſters prayer in the pulpit; If he will ſett it too againe, be it at his pleaſure, it may be to his perill.</p>
                  <p>Wee have queſtioned it very much, and endeavoured to put it out of queſtion, that <hi>John</hi> did not teach his Diſciples to pray by giving them formes of prayer to ſay. Wee have cleared it to be a parents dutie to teach his child to pray; and, as wee could, wee have directed his practiſe, and concluded, That a parent tea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cheth not his child to pray, that gives him formes of prayer to ſay, for that they learne without teaching, too prompt and ready that way. The Spirit of the Lord teacheth parent and child to pray; and the firſt thing the Spirit teacheth, wee thinke, is, to ſay that they <hi>cannot pray;</hi> yet wee ſhould tempt God, if wee our ſelves ſhould not pray, and teach our children ſo to doe, to pray, that they may be enabled to pray. To ſhutt up, The God of all graces and father of mercies, in and through His Sonne, gives forth no temporall, much leſſe eternall ſalvation; no common mercy, much leſſe any ſpirituall grace, which is eternall, to His <hi>marve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>louſly</hi>
                     <note place="margin">Pſal. 4. 3.</note> 
                     <hi>ſeperated ones, His gratious Saints,</hi> but He will ſtirre them up to <hi>inquire</hi> after Him firſt before He gives it; They ſhall aske before they have; and but aske, and have, yet not for their asking.</p>
                  <p>Now it is marvelous to conſider <hi>Satans deviſes</hi> here, that im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>placable enemy and adverſary of all righteouſneſſe He perſwades
<pb n="75" facs="tcp:117967:40"/> the wicked to ſit downe fully content with their condition, and ſatisfied with common mercies, and not pray at all; and if they will be praying; it ſhall be but <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                        <desc>•</desc>
                     </gap>prating and babling; A meere prophaneing of Gods Name, if not blaſpheming. If they will pray as the moſt will, they ſhall pray in anothers words, and no matter in whoſe <hi>name;</hi> by a booke or without it, by the memorie, never with the heart, unleſſe for the remooving of ſome plague, felt or feared. But never about the <hi>plague of the heart,</hi> the plague indeed.</p>
                  <p>And for theſe <hi>gratious Saints,</hi> This adverſary ſhewes himſelfe ſuch an one, in no one thing more than in this, <hi>To keepe them from praying</hi> but if that cannot be, then he imployes all his force poli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cie and might to hinder and interrupt prayer, and for the effecting of this—what will he caſt in; and how readily doth fleſh com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ply with him<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> But theſe know <hi>whom they have truſted;</hi> And that His grace ſhall be ſufficient for them.</p>
                  <closer>AMEN.</closer>
               </div>
            </div>
         </div>
      </body>
      <back>
         <div type="postscript">
            <head>Poſtſcript.</head>
            <p>WEE have purpoſely forborne to diſcharge our Treatiſe of that charge of blaſphemie once and againe charged upon it; wee have given a marke in the margine all along where the yong-man, in the name perhaps of his elders, enters not his diſſent onely but the charge of blaſphemie againſt us. It is hum<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly referred to God and His Scriptures to judge how juſt that charge is. And if it ſhall pleaſe thoſe <hi>whom God hath made able Miniſters of the New Teſtament, not of the Leter but of the Spirit</hi> (for <hi>the letter killeth but the Spirit giveth life</hi>) to give-in thei<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap> judgement here alſo, we are aſſured it ſhall be according to Truth. Wee will adde two words more; The one we borrow from him, whoſe words we ſhall hereafter ſet downe; <hi>It is far more facile to give the hardeſt Cenſures,</hi> than <hi>to Anſwer the eaſieſt Arguments.</hi> The other is this which one of us has read ſome where; <hi>A good Cauſe when plainely told is learnedly pleaded, eſpecially if a Meeke</hi> Moſes <hi>or juſt</hi> Joſhua <hi>be the Judge thereof.</hi> So we come to ſet downe here, as was ſpecified upon the <hi>Title page,</hi> the words of that holy and learned Man, who ſpeakes to all matters he undertakes <hi>in the Name of his God</hi> to ſpeake unto <hi>after his manner, which is to ſay all
<pb n="76" facs="tcp:117967:41"/> that can be ſaid in any ſubject whatſoever.</hi> This <hi>encomie</hi> or high Commendations was given to <hi>Grotius</hi> by one of our own, in ſome matters of the higheſt concernment, relating to our deare Lord and Chriſt, of the ſame perſwaſion<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> with him; And ſo thought it not enough to Commend the ſaid man <hi>without any exception,</hi> but he muſt admire him alſo <hi>ſine modo</hi> and without juſt reaſon. May it not be feared, That he <hi>feareth not his Maker</hi> as he ought, nor Conſiders how <hi>ſoone He can take him away<g ref="char:punc">▪</g>
               </hi> who can give ſuch flattering words, or high commendations to that man, who hath ſuch low thoughts of our deareſt <hi>Lord</hi> and <hi>Saviour.</hi> To ſay no more; Surely ſuch an honour as this <hi>to ſay what can be ſaid in any ſubject</hi> belongs to that Man, who <hi>honours God,</hi> and whom God doth honour; whoſe whole heart is taken-up with the <hi>love of Him;</hi> his tongue with the <hi>praiſe of Him;</hi> and whole life with <hi>the ſer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vice of Him;</hi> And bleſſed be our God and Father of our Lord Jeſus Chriſt, who <hi>giveth gifts unto Men,</hi> plenty of his Spirit, and variety of His Graces, <hi>for the perfecting of His Saints; for the worke of the Miniſtry; and for the edifying of the Body of Christ.</hi> Having ſpoken this which every man, we thinke, that hath read all, or any part of this learned mans works, as one amongſt us hath done, will find himſelfe preſſed to ſpeake, and ſo give that honour to the ſaid excellent Man, <hi>to ſay what can be ſaid in any ſubject</hi> his God ſhall ingage him upon. We ſhall now ſett downe what he ſaith for the readers fuller reſolution, eſpecially to the fourth <hi>Query,</hi> relating to the Lords prayer, as was ſpecified in the Title page.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Q. ii. Did not Chriſt preſcribe a forme of prayer to his diſciples, ſo that there remaineth no doubt touching the lawfulnes of uſing a form?</hi>
            </p>
            <p>A. Luk. 11. 1, 2, 3, 4.</p>
            <p>
               <hi>Anſ.</hi> If Chriſt preſcribed a <hi>forme of prayer</hi> to his diſciples, to be uſed <hi>as a forme</hi> by the repetition of the ſame words; I confeſſe it will be out of Queſtion, that it is lawfull to uſe a forme: but that it is lawfull not to uſe a forme, or that a man may uſe any prayer but a forme, on that ſuppoſition, will not be ſo eaſily determined. The words of Chriſt are, <hi>when you pray, ſay, Our Father &amp;c.</hi> If in this preſcription, not the <hi>matter</hi> onely, but the <hi>words</hi> alſo are at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tended, and that forme of them which followes is preſcribed to be uſed, by vertue of this command of Chriſt, it will be hard to diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cover
<pb n="77" facs="tcp:117967:41"/> on what ground we may <hi>any otherwiſe</hi> pray, ſeing our S<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>
               <g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours command is poſitive, <hi>when you pray, ſay, Our Father, &amp;c.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>That which M. B. is to prove is, that <hi>Our Saviour hath preſcri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bed the repetition of the ſame words enſuing,</hi> and when he hath done ſo, if ſo be he can do, his concluſion muſt be, that <hi>that forme ought to be uſed,</hi> not at all that <hi>any elſe</hi> may. If our Saviour have pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed us <hi>a forme,</hi> how ſhall any man dare to <hi>preſcribe another?</hi> or can any man do it without caſting on his <hi>forme</hi> the reproach of <hi>imperfection</hi> and inſufficiency? Our Saviour hath preſcribed us a <hi>forme of prayer</hi> to be uſed as a forme by the repetition of the ſame words; therefore we may uſe it, yea we muſt, is an invinci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble argument, on ſuppoſition of the truth of the propoſition. But our Saviour hath preſcribed us ſuch a <hi>forme &amp;c.</hi> therefore we may uſe another, which he hath not preſcribed, hath neither <hi>ſhew</hi> nor <hi>colour</hi> of Reaſon in it.</p>
            <p>But how will M. B. prove that Chriſt doth not here inſtruct his Diſciples in <hi>what</hi> they ought to pray for, and for <hi>what</hi> they ought in prayer to addreſſe themſelves to God, and <hi>under what</hi> conſiderations they are to looke on God in their approaches to him, and the like, only, but alſo that he preſcribes <hi>the words</hi> there mentioned by him to be repeated by them in their ſupplications. <hi>Luk:</hi> 11<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> he bids them ſay <hi>Our Father &amp;c.</hi> which at large <hi>Mat:</hi> 6. is, <hi>pray after this manner:</hi> 
               <gap reason="foreign">
                  <desc>〈 in non-Latin alphabet 〉</desc>
               </gap> 
               <hi>to this purpoſe.</hi> I doe not thinke the Prophet preſcribes a <hi>forme of words,</hi> to be uſed by the Church when he ſayes, <hi>Take with you words, and turne to the Lord, and ſay unto him, Take away iniquitie,</hi> (Hoſ: 14. 2) but rather calls them to <hi>fervent ſupplication</hi> for the pardon of ſin, as God ſhould enable them to deale with him. And though the Apoſtles never prayd for any thing, but what they were for the ſubſtance di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rected to by this prayer of our Saviour, yet we doe not find, that ever they <hi>repeated</hi> the very words here mentioned, or once com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>manded or preſcribed the uſe of them, to any of the <hi>Saints</hi> in their dayes, whom they exhorted to pray ſo fervently and ear<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſtly. Nor in any of the <hi>Rules</hi> and Directions, that are given for our praying<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> either in reference to our ſelves, or him by whom we have acceſſe to God, is the uſe of theſe words at any time in the leaſt <hi>recommended</hi> to us, or recalled to mind, as a matter of dutie.</p>
            <pb n="78" facs="tcp:117967:42"/>
            <p>Our Saviour ſayes when ye pray, <hi>ſay, Our Father;</hi> on ſuppoſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion of the ſence contended for, and that a <hi>forme</hi> of words is <hi>preſcribed,</hi> I aske whether we may at any time pray, and <hi>not ſay</hi> ſo? ſeeing he ſayes, <hi>when you pray,</hi> ſay: whether we <hi>may ſay any thing elſe,</hi> or uſe any other words? whether the ſaying of theſe <hi>words</hi> be a part of the worſhip of God? Or whether any <hi>promiſe</hi> of <hi>Acceptation</hi> be annexed to the ſaying ſo? whether the <hi>ſpirit of grace</hi> and <hi>ſupplication</hi> be not <hi>promiſed</hi> to all beleivers? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther he be not given them to enable them to pray, both as to <hi>matter</hi> and <hi>manner?</hi> and if ſo, whether the Repetition of the words mentioned by them, <hi>who have not the Spirit given them</hi> for the ends before mentioned, be availeable? and whether <hi>prayer by the Spirit</hi> where theſe words are not repeated, as to the <hi>letters</hi> and <hi>Syllables,</hi> and order wherein they ſtand, be acceptable to God? whether the preſcription of a <hi>forme</hi> of words, and the gift of a <hi>ſpirit</hi> of prayer be conſiſtent? whether the forme be pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcribed becauſe Believers are not able to pray without it? Or be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe there is a peculiar Holineſſe force and <hi>energy</hi> in the letters words and ſyllables, as they ſtand in that forme? And whe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther to ſay the firſt of thoſe be not derogatory to the Glory of God, and <hi>efficacy of the Spirit,</hi> promiſed and given to Believers<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> and the ſecond, to <hi>aſſert</hi> the uſing of a Charme in the worſhip of God? whether in that reſpect <hi>Pater n<gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                     <desc>•</desc>
                  </gap>ſter</hi> be not as good as <hi>Our Father?</hi> whether innumerable <hi>poore ſo<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> les</hi> are not deluded and hardned by <hi>ſatisfying</hi> their conſciences in, and with, the uſe of this forme never knowing what it is to pray in the <hi>holy Ghoſt?</hi> And whether the Aſſerting this forme of words to be uſed have not confirmed many in their <hi>Atheiſticall</hi> blaſpheming of the <hi>holy Spirit</hi> of God, and his Grace in the prayers of his people? And whether the repetition of theſe words, after men have been long praying for the things contained in them, <gap reason="illegible" resp="#KEYERS" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>s the manner of ſome is, be not ſo <hi>remote</hi> from any <hi>pretence</hi> or colour of <hi>warrant</hi> in the Scripture, as that it is in plaine termes <hi>ridiculous?</hi> When M. <hi>Biddle,</hi> or any on his behalfe, hath anſwered theſe queſtions, they may be ſupplyed with more of the like nature and impor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tance.</p>
            <trailer>An End.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:117967:42"/>
         </div>
      </back>
   </text>
</TEI>
